<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Gospel preached to the Romans, in four sermons two on the 5th of November, and two on the 30th of January, 1680 / by John Cave ...</title>
            <author>Cave, John, d. 1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17526</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12281848</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12281848</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58738</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31403)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58738)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 624:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Gospel preached to the Romans, in four sermons two on the 5th of November, and two on the 30th of January, 1680 / by John Cave ...</title>
                  <author>Cave, John, d. 1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>108, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for Rich. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans I, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58738:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GOSPEL Preached to the ROMANS, IN FOUR SERMONS.</p>
            <p>Two on the <hi>5th</hi> of <hi>November:</hi> AND Two on the <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1680.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN CAVE,</hi> Rector of <hi>Cold-Orton</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter-ſhire;</hi> and Chaplain to the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Durham.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Fruamur bono noſtro, &amp; recti ſententiam tempere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, cohibeatur Superſtitio, impietas expietur, vera religio reſervetur.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Min. Fael. p. 55.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>Rich. Chiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> at the Roſe and Crown in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermons">
            <pb facs="tcp:58738:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58738:2"/>
            <head>THE GOSPEL Preached to the ROMANS, IN TWO SERMONS, On <hi>November</hi> 5. 1680.</head>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <head>The Firſt Sermon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ROM. 1.15.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>So, as much as in me is, I am ready to preach the Goſpel to you that are at <hi>Rome</hi> alſo.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe great Doctor of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> directs this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to all the Profeſſors of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> tempering his <hi>Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Authority,</hi> with much Charity, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rdor, inſinuating his good Opinion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58738:3"/>of their Sincerity, tho attended with the Weakneſs and Imperfection of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, who are uſually too retentive of their former Prejudices, and Prepoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and therefore ſtand in need of clear Demonſtrations, and frequent Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, to bring them off from a Religion delivered and endeared to them by <hi>Tradition from their Fathers,</hi> and to confirm and eſtabliſh them in a new Doctrine.</p>
               <p>After he had magnified his own Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, by intimating his extraordinary Call and <hi>Separation unto the Goſpel of God in the firſt verſe of this Chapter;</hi> that he might not any ways advance himſelf, to the diſcouragement of their Infant-Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and hopeful Diſpoſitions; he owns them alſo to be the <hi>Called of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in another Capacity,<note place="margin">Ver. 6.</note> and dignifies them with the Titles of the <hi>Beloved of God</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 7.8.</note> ſuch as he <hi>gave Thanks and prayed for,</hi> in regard of their Chriſtian Principles, which made <hi>Rome</hi> now more truly renowned, and honourably <hi>ſpoken of throughout the World,</hi> than all he former Grandeur, Wiſdom, and Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oecumenius</hi> gives this Reaſon of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> precedency of this Epiſtle, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58738:3"/>was written to ſuch, as had not only the advantage of a Civil and Philoſophical Education, but were alſo initiated in the Worſhip of the true God, according to the Revelations of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> yet to keep them humble and teachable, he ſuggeſts to them their want of many things, of ſome <hi>Spiritual Gift,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 11.</note> in order to the Settlement, and Growth of their Faith and Comfort; the fructifying of their fair Bloſſoms, and the ripening of their tender Fruit:<note place="margin">Ver. 13.</note> I have <hi>oftentimes pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to come unto you, that I might have ſome Fruit among you alſo, even as among other</hi> Gentiles. For the Doctrines I teach, are ſuch, as will not only <hi>give Wiſdom to the Simple,</hi> and Barbarous, but improve the Knowledg of the <hi>Wiſe;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in that reſpect, as fit to be preached at <hi>Athens,</hi> or at <hi>Rome,</hi> as in the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and ignorant parts of the World; yea ſuch are your defects in Knowledg and Faith, that I am obliged, by my Commiſſion, to inſtruct you; <hi>I am a Debtor both to the</hi> Greeks, <hi>and</hi> Barbarians; <hi>to the Wiſe, and to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwiſe. So, as much as in me is, I am ready to preach the Goſpel to you that are at</hi> Rome <hi>alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58738:4"/>
               <p>From theſe Words, ſome have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Chearfulneſs, and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, his <hi>Readineſs</hi> and Reſolution, in diſcharge of his <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> as a Pattern worthy to be imitated by all of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Calling; for as much as neither the Power, nor Prejudices of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Seat of the World's Empire, and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, did in the leaſt diſhearten him from Preaching the <hi>Goſpel</hi> there: <hi>Where</hi> the <hi>Articles</hi> of pure <hi>Faith,</hi> and the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveable, or at leaſt, inexplicable My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> were more likely to be rejected with ſcorn, than <hi>received in Love;</hi> and where ſuch a plain Preacher, as came not in the way of <hi>Human Wiſdom,</hi> or <hi>Excellencies</hi> of Speech, was like to perſwade but little; yet <hi>he is ready,</hi> and reſolved as God ſhall enable him, as <hi>much as in him is,</hi> to <hi>preach</hi> this <hi>Goſpel at Rome;</hi> as he ſpeaks Emphatically, <hi>at Rome alſo;</hi> a Place ſo famous, for the general Concourſe of the Wiſe and knowing Men of the World.</p>
               <p>I cannot diſallow of this Sence of the Words, which would afford us very profitable matter of Diſcourſe; yet I humbly conceive, they are very capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of another Meaning, <hi>viz.</hi> That our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58738:4"/>Apoſtle, was the more deſirous to <hi>preach the Goſpel at</hi> Rome, becauſe there was ſtill a great mixture of <hi>Judaiſme,</hi> and <hi>Gentiliſme,</hi> even in the Chriſtianity of that Place; and thoſe that he calls <hi>Saints,</hi> were but imperfectly ſuch, right in Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals, but in many reſpects need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reformation of their Errors, as well as Settlement, and firmer grounding in the true Belief.</p>
               <p>Though St. <hi>Peter</hi> were the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and each ſuperintended their proper <hi>Dioceſs</hi> in all places where they met; as at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and afterwards at <hi>Rome,</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining diſtinct <hi>Biſhops</hi> to ſucceed in both Cities; and making all the <hi>Jews</hi> in each under the Charge of one, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> of another; (as the Learned Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> hath abundantly proved, to the utter overthrow of St <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy,</hi> and Univerſal Paſtorſhip:) yet as St. <hi>Peter,</hi> before any Agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween themſelves to the contrary, preaches the <hi>Goſpel to Cornelius a Gentile,</hi> and his Family. So St. <hi>Paul</hi> here writes to <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> both, and deſires to have an opportunity to <hi>preach the Goſpel</hi> to them in common.</p>
               <p>He had upon ſeveral Occaſions en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58738:5"/>the <hi>Jews</hi> in their <hi>Synagogues,</hi> and diſputed with the <hi>Greeks</hi> in their moſt famous <hi>Cities;</hi> at <hi>Athens, Corinth, Epheſus,</hi> and elſewhere; erecting where ever he came, ſome honourable Trophies of the Power and Prevalency of his Maſter's <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He deſires now to carry his Spiritual Arms, and Forces, to the <hi>Imperial City,</hi> not to make himſelf, but <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, and victorious; to triumph not only over the Vices, and Immoralities, but the very <hi>Religion,</hi> or rather, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of <hi>Superſtition</hi> in that Place, by ſhewing them how weak the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, and how altogether ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual the Precepts of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy were, to make Men truly happy; that neither <hi>Gentiles</hi> by their Natural Works, nor <hi>Jews</hi> by their Legal Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, could be juſtified: but yet both were equally capable of <hi>Salvation</hi> by the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which he is ſo ready to <hi>preach</hi> to them. It hath been obſerved, that in all the <hi>Churches</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtle's</hi> own <hi>plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and cultivation, the Seeds of ſound and wholeſom Doctrine did more eaſily take Root, than <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> and <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cuſtoms could be <hi>extirpated;</hi> and by his diſtinct Addreſſes, both to <hi>Jews</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58738:5"/>
                  <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in this <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> we may well conceive, this was one great inducement to him to preach the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> to them that were at <hi>Rome alſo, viz.</hi> To bring them off from thoſe <hi>Superſtitions</hi> which <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality,</hi> and <hi>Oral Tradition,</hi> had made them too fond of.</p>
               <p>But if we will ſuppoſe thoſe <hi>Chriſtian Converts</hi> to be refined, and wholly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from all their former Errors, and Corruptions, and ſo not to need the <hi>preaching of the Goſpel,</hi> for thoſe Purpoſes; It is moſt plain, that there were a great many <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> among them, to whom this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> was to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, and that many of them, who could by the Light of Nature eaſily diſcover a God, and a Providence; yet were fallen into <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and ſuch vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Practices, that they much wanted the <hi>preaching of the Goſpel;</hi> a clearer Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the Juſtice and Goodneſs of God to recover them.</p>
               <p>It is not my Deſign at preſent, to make a Compariſon of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> with the <hi>Ethnical,</hi> or <hi>Judaical</hi> Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, and to ſhew the great Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges it hath of them, both in reſpect of its Rules, its Aids, Motives and Terms of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, its <hi>Power</hi> and Efficacy to <hi>ſave.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58738:6"/>
               <p>Nor ſhall I enquire further into the State of <hi>Rome</hi> at that time, nor what mixtures of their former Sentiments and Practices they retained, who came from the <hi>Synagogue,</hi> or from the <hi>Temples</hi> of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and <hi>Apollo,</hi> into the Diſcipline of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Services of his <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I ſhall regard only the Condition of our Modern <hi>Romans,</hi> and muſt apply that Doctrine to you, for your Defence, and Security, in the Truth; which for their Conviction and Recovery, <hi>I am ready, as much as in me is, to preach to them that are at</hi> Rome <hi>alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In my Diſcourſe upon theſe Words, I ſhall confine my ſelf to three general Heads; ſhewing firſt of all,
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>That the <hi>Romans</hi> now ſtand in as much need, if not more, of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the Goſpel, as they did in our Apoſtle's Days.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>That the moſt Chriſtian and effectual may of promoting the Goſpel, is Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Perſwaſion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>That thoſe who are commiſſionated to that Office, ought to be ready, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58738:6"/>reſolute in the diſcharge of it.</hi> Of theſe in their Order, beginning with the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>That the</hi> Romans <hi>now ſtand in as much need, if not more, of the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, as they did in our Apoſtle's Days.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt dark and depraved ſtate of <hi>Gentiliſme,</hi> did not more want the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> the purifying Light of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> the <hi>preaching</hi> of <hi>Repentance from dead Works,</hi> and Holineſs of Life, than this pretended <hi>Catholick Church</hi> now doth; For not only the <hi>Romana,</hi> but the <hi>Germana Fides,</hi> the noted Honeſty and Fidelity of thoſe <hi>Heathens,</hi> is in a manner quite loſt among thoſe <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and their preſent <hi>Treachery,</hi> and <hi>Perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> are as much <hi>ſpoken of,</hi> and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced <hi>throughout the World,</hi> as their <hi>Primitive Faith</hi> then was.</p>
               <p>Perhaps there were as many, if not more <hi>Saints,</hi> in <hi>Nero</hi>'s <hi>Houſhold,</hi> as are in his <hi>Holineſs</hi>'s own Family, and the places neareſt his Influence and Inſpection; Which gave the famous <hi>Van-Harmin</hi> occaſion to declare;<note place="margin">In <hi>Vitâ</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minii.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That, if he had not before been ſufficiently averſe to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58738:7"/>
                     <hi>Popery,</hi> the ſight of <hi>Rome,</hi> and its lewd Practices, would have given him an invincible diſlike.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall not here take notice of what hath been ſaid by their own Authors, of the <hi>Epicurean</hi> and <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> Lives of ſo many <hi>Popes,</hi> ſcarce to be parallell'd in any <hi>heatheniſh</hi> Hiſtory; nor of the Stews, and tolerated Debauches of <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf. Neither ſhould I have touched at all upon this <hi>Argument,</hi> wherein we our ſelves have too great a Concern, if it were not moſt apparent, that <hi>their</hi> vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Manners,</hi> are the proper Fruit of their corrupt <hi>Doctrines:</hi> Thoſe I mean, of <hi>Equivocation, Mental Reſervation, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing with Oaths,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Durand. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>dist.</hi> 31.</note> 
                  <hi>breaking Faith with Hereticks, &amp;c.</hi> And thoſe other of <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, Vendible Pardons,</hi> eaſy <hi>Abſolutions,</hi> and <hi>Death-Bed Repentance;</hi> particularly their making Fornication leſs ſinful in ſome, than chaſt Wedlock, and not a <hi>deadly Sin</hi> in any, according to the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The manifold Diſorders of our Lives, the great Luxuriancy of Vice, and the decay of <hi>Piety, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Sobriety</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe of our own Communion, require a pathetick and powerful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, of all the Holy Precepts, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58738:7"/>Reproofs, Directions of our <hi>bleſſed Saviour,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſtill to preach <hi>Goſpel-Reformation</hi> to the moſt <hi>reformed</hi> part of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> where all the Principles of Vertue are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſufficiently taught, and eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>But where it is a part of Mens <hi>Religion</hi> to be vicious, where it is their Duty to <hi>Sin,</hi> and their wicked <hi>Practices</hi> derive from ſuch <hi>Principles</hi> ſuch impious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines as make a kind of <hi>Anti-Goſpel</hi> to that of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> their Spiritual E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is very neceſſitous and deplorable; they want <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as well as <hi>Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> the <hi>planting</hi> of <hi>Paul,</hi> no leſs than the <hi>waterings</hi> of <hi>Apollo:</hi> Which minds me to proceed, to the principal thing I intend to inſiſt upon, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew,</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Church of</hi> Rome <hi>ſtands in much need of the preaching of our Saviour's pure Goſpel,</hi> in regard of the <hi>Heatheniſm,</hi> (if I may not ſay) <hi>Anti-Chriſtianiſm,</hi> of ſeveral <hi>Religious Tenents, Opinions, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> retained, and obſerved among them.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">There is no Branch of implanted <hi>Superſtition</hi> in any Son of <hi>Adam,</hi> which may not ſufficiently feed it ſelf with ſome part or other of the <hi>Romiſh Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> or with ſome Cuſtoms by that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58738:8"/>
                     <hi>Church</hi> allowed, concerning the <hi>Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints, Adoration of Reliques, Worſhip of Images,</hi>
                  </q> or the like; as the learned Dr. <hi>Jackson</hi> obſerves. And what was ſpoken more generally by him, I ſhall endeavour to demonſtrate parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly.</p>
               <p>But before I come to ſpeak of their <hi>Opinions</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> give me leave to obſerve; That the very <hi>Characters</hi> and <hi>Marks</hi> of their <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Titles</hi> and <hi>Prerogatives</hi> of their <hi>Popes,</hi> are ſuch, if not the very ſame, that the Heathens ſignalized themſelves, and their High-Prieſt by. I begin with <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s firſt note of the <hi>Church,</hi> and that is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Catholiciſm,</hi> or Univerſality, which (ſince the Goſpel hath been preached throughout the World, and both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> are made one in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are baptized into one Body) is no improper <hi>Mark</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> but very falſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied by the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> to themſelves; and with an Arrogance no where to be equalled, but among the proud <hi>Pagans,</hi> who boaſted of nothing more than the Latitude of their <hi>Superſtition,</hi> and that they only were true <hi>Catholicks;</hi> that all <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> was <hi>theirs;</hi> that the <hi>Jews</hi> were ignorant of the Gods of their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58738:8"/>
                  <hi>Fathers;</hi> obſerved the Inſtitutions of a <hi>private Spirit,</hi> a <hi>Lawgiver</hi> of a <hi>ſingular</hi> and <hi>ſeparating</hi> Humour; and therefore were no better than downright <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> a <hi>Sect</hi> diſtinct from, and contrary unto the <hi>Religion</hi> of the whole World beſides; which is no more in effect than what <hi>Tacitus,</hi> one of their wiſeſt and moſt ſober Writers affirms; <hi>quo ſibi in poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum gentem firmaret, novos ritus contrarioſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cateris mortalibus indidit; Moſes,</hi> ſaith he, that he might have a People of his own, inſtructed that Nation in <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> quite contrary to thoſe which were generally received.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">They prophane thoſe things which we eſteem Holy,<note place="margin">Profana illie omnia quae a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud nos ſacra.</note> and they tolerate what we prohibit.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Hitherto you ſee, who thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> if not the <hi>Roman-Catholicks</hi> in thoſe days; for to note this by the way, it will be very hard to make Sence of the compoſition, by any other <hi>Figure</hi> than that which they uſed, when they denoted abſolute Univerſality, by <hi>Romanus Orbis,</hi> and <hi>Romanum Imperium;</hi> and made <hi>Romanitas</hi> to ſignify the whole World, only that which they called <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baria</hi> excepted; <hi>Romana Dominatio,</hi> i. e. <hi>Humani Generis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Florus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58738:9"/>
               <p n="2">2. Another Mark of the Church is <hi>Antiquity,</hi> which they much glory in, as if theirs were truly <hi>antient,</hi> and ours a <hi>novel,</hi> upſtart <hi>Religion.</hi> Notwithſtanding our learned Writers, have abundantly ſhewed, not only, when the Errors we proteſt againſt, were not in the <hi>Church,</hi> but the particular time, and occaſion of the commencement of many of them, tho not a few of thoſe <hi>Tares,</hi> were ſown in the moſt ignorant and ſleepy Ages, and brought forth by ſuch gradual Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations, that they might not ſo eaſily be diſcerned in their Productions and Progreſs, as in their Maturity; but this is beſides our preſent undertaking, which was only to ſhew that this Pretence alſo, was a great ſupport of <hi>Gentiliſme.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Si longa aetas authoritatem Religionibus conciliat, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanda eſt tot ſaeculis Fides, &amp; ſequendi ſunt nobis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes qui ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuti ſunt ſaeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer ſuos. <hi>Symmachi.</hi> Ep. ad <hi>Theod.</hi>
                  </note> Its Orators and Advocates upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſet forth the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of their <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and the <hi>Innovations</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> Where was your Religion before <hi>Luther?</hi> ſay the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to us; and where was yours before <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth?</hi> ſaid the <hi>Pagans</hi> to the firſt <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> When<note n="†" place="margin">Acts 17.19.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> preached the <hi>Goſpel</hi> at <hi>Athens,</hi> the Philoſophers there asked in Scorn, <hi>What the new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was, whereof he ſpake?</hi> and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58738:9"/>
                  <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> calls the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſtianos genus homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num novae &amp; maleficae ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitionis. <hi>Tacit. Annal.</hi> lib. 15. <hi>Bellarm.</hi> lib. 4. de Not. Eccleſiae. cap. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Men of a new and miſchievous Superſtition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. A third <hi>Mark</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> which they think ſuits theirs very well, is a <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Working Miracles:</hi> we cannot yield, that this is a perpetual viſible Note of the true <hi>Church,</hi> as is pretended.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miracles</hi> indeed are the cleareſt Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of <hi>Divine Truth</hi> and Authority, and the moſt immediate <hi>Credentials</hi> of <hi>Heaven.</hi> Our <hi>bleſſed Saviour</hi> atteſted his <hi>Divinity,</hi> and the <hi>Truth</hi> of his <hi>Goſpel</hi> thereby, and in the <hi>Churches</hi> Infancy, gave his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> the ſame Power of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming their <hi>Doctrine:</hi> but many good Reaſons have been given to ſhew, that there is not the ſame need, and uſe of them now, as then there was; and how far the Devil by the Agility, and Subtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his <hi>Nature,</hi> may impoſe upon the Senſes of Men, and puzzle them with ſtrange Appearances, I ſhall not now enquire; nor endeavour to refute the pretence of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> in this kind, by diſcovering the Vanity and Extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of their <hi>lying Legends,</hi> only to be named, in a place, and time fitter for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58738:10"/>Laughter and Diſport, than this where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are. Nor ſhall I ſtay to ſhew, how little cauſe they have to boaſt of this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, if they were more expert in it, than indeed they are; Seeing our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> have propheſied of the <hi>latter times,</hi> that in a general <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> from the <hi>Faith, Great Wonders ſhould be wrought,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 24.24.</note> 
                  <hi>able to deceive, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, the very Elect;</hi> and that thoſe eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially who would <hi>not receive the Love of the Truth, thro' an effectual working of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.9, 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>in lying Wonders, and ſtrong Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſhould be brought to believe Lies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But my Buſineſs here alſo is to ſhew, that the <hi>Heathens</hi> talked as much, and upon as good Grounds, of this Gift of <hi>Miracles,</hi> as they do; it is well known how famous <hi>Pythagoras</hi> was for it, in the Writings of <hi>Porphyry,</hi> and <hi>Apollonius, Tyaneus,</hi> in thoſe of <hi>Philostratus,</hi> and <hi>Hierocles;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiſtor. <hi>lib.</hi> 4.</note> beſides what is ſaid of <hi>Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> by <hi>Tacitus,</hi> and thoſe wonderful Manifeſtations of the Divine Power, and Preſence in the <hi>Roman Armies,</hi> which <hi>Balbus</hi> boaſted of:<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de nat. Deorum. <hi>p. 27.</hi>
                  </note> yea the idle and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Reports, of the frequent remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals of the Chappel of <hi>Loretto,</hi> from one Country, and from one Place to another, by inviſible Hands, in its moſt creditable
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58738:10"/>Appearance, ſeems to be but the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-part of a <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> Wonder; That, I mean, of the Temple of <hi>Diana</hi>'s remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val out of the Iſle of <hi>Zazinthus,</hi> unto <hi>Saguntum</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> as it is related by <hi>Pliny.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Another <hi>Mark</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> with them, is outward Splendor and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Proſperity; of which we read no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and it agrees much better with the Condition of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> and <hi>Mahumetaniſm,</hi> than this of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</hi> The <hi>Roman Orator,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cicer. Orat. <hi>de Haruſpic.</hi>
                  </note> from the flouriſhing Greatneſs, the many Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Triumphs of that <hi>Empire,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Truth and Goodneſs of its Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and the <hi>Idolatrous Jews,</hi> will not be put out of conceit with their abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <hi>Superſtitions,</hi> becauſe they proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and fared well in them;<note place="margin">Jer. 44.17.</note> 
                  <hi>We will certainly do whatſoever thing goeth out of our Mouth, to burn Incenſe to the Queen of Heaven, and to pour out Drink-Offerings to her, as we have done, we and our Fathers, our Kings, and our Princes in the Cities of</hi> Judah, <hi>and in the Streets of</hi> Jeruſalem. But why ſo reſolute and obſtinate in your way? Why? Becauſe we have this <hi>Catholick Argument</hi> that we are in the right outward Plenty, Health and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58738:11"/>Proſperity, as it follows; <hi>for then had we plenty of Victuals, and were well, and ſaw no evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might here add, That the <hi>Heathens</hi> have the ſame plea with them, for <hi>unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted Continuance, Number,</hi> and <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety</hi> of <hi>Profeſſors:</hi> but I forbear this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is no reproach to true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> that they are a <hi>little Flock,</hi> ſeeing we are aſſured by Scripture Teſtimony that <hi>the whole World</hi> in a manner lies in Wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>I proceed to examine the <hi>Popes</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Titles of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi> It hath been obſerved that <hi>old Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> who was the Foundreſs of <hi>Idols,</hi> and the Mother of all <hi>Heatheniſh Superſtitions,</hi> was the firſt Pattern in the World of <hi>ambitious Dominion.</hi> And,</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the Supremacy of our new and myſtical <hi>Babel,</hi> it ſeems to derive from that <hi>Lordſhip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark 10.42.</note> which was exerciſed by thoſe that ruled over the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> And indeed that Authority which the <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> attributes to the <hi>Pontifex Maximus,</hi> may ſuit <hi>new Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dionyſ. Halic.</hi> Ant. Rom. l. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> as well as old. <q rend="margQuotes">The <hi>High Prieſts</hi> have great power among the <hi>Romans,</hi> and are the Lords and Controllers of their moſt important Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; they decide all Religious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58738:11"/>between the Commonalty, the <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> and the <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> they call all Magiſtrates and Prieſts to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for the exerciſe of their <hi>Authority.</hi>
                  </q> And what follows in the ſame Author, ſhews, in how great repute they were.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For their Infallibility. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. They determine all Differences, relating either to <hi>Traditional</hi> or <hi>Novel</hi> Cuſtoms in Religion. I know the Papiſts would fain parallel the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of their Chair with that of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and endeavour to confirm it by a ſeeming Parity of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in their caſe with that of the <hi>Jews, Thou ſhalt come to the Prieſts, the Levites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 17.9, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Judg that ſhall be in thoſe days, &amp;c. Thou ſhalt not decline from the Sentence that they ſhall ſhew thee, to the right Hand, nor to the left.</hi> But it is apparent, they were to judg according to Law; and therefore the <hi>Jewiſh Gloſs</hi> would fit theſe Men's Purpoſe,<note place="margin">Gloſſa Hebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ica.</note> better than the Text it ſelf, <hi>If the Judg ſhall tell thee that the right Hand is the left, and the left the right, thou muſt believe him.</hi> To which that known Saying of <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s very well agrees, <hi>If the Pope ſhall deſine Vertue to be Vice, and Vice Vertue, we muſt take it to be ſo upon his Credit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58738:12"/>
               <p>But I proceed to examine the <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Practices, Opinions</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and to compare them with thoſe of the <hi>Heathens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I muſt not enlarge upon Particulars, becauſe I have ſo many to name, but ſhall be moſt brief in thoſe that are of an obvious and ordinary Obſervation. I begin with;</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Canonization of Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here the <hi>Pope</hi> aſſumes the very ſame Authority which the <hi>Roman Senate</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged in the <hi>Apotheoſis</hi> of their <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</hi> As will appear, by comparing the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Rites</hi> of <hi>Canonization</hi> in <hi>Bellarmin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bellarmin de Sanctorum Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitudine. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7. Alexand. ab Alex. Genial. dies Herod. Hiſt. Rom. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Dr.</hi> Jackſon<hi>'s Works, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 937.</note> with thoſe of the <hi>Gentile Conſecrations:</hi> Yea to make the Parallel more compleat, as the <hi>Deification</hi> of <hi>Antinous</hi> was countenanced with feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Relations, and the appearance of a new Star; So are Revelations frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pretended, to credit the <hi>Popiſh Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications;</hi> and ſurely where <hi>Reaſon</hi> doth not only deſert, but oppoſe them, as in this caſe of making their <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>Mediators,</hi> they had need be well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with <hi>Revelations.</hi> The ſecond thing I ſhall inſtance in, is,</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:58738:12"/>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Their praying to Saints and Angels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which ſeems to be the very ſame thing condemned by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the Revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the latter times, under the title of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which we tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate <hi>Doctrine of Devils;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1.</note> but the moſt learned Mr. <hi>Joſeph Mede,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Apoſtacy of the latter times.</note> 
                  <hi>Doctrines of Demons.</hi> Theſe <hi>Demons</hi> in the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> Divinity, were an inferiour fort of <hi>Deified</hi> Powers, Mediating Spirits betwixt the <hi>Supream Deities</hi> and mortal Men, according to that of <hi>Plato,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plato's Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſion.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. God doth not mix himſelf with Men by any immediate Communications, but all Converſe, and Conference between the <hi>Gods,</hi> i. e. the <hi>Dii ſuperi,</hi> the Superiour Gods and us is managed by <hi>Demons.</hi> They receive and preſent our Prayers, they return our Bleſſings, and confer our Rewards. <q rend="margQuotes">And it is <hi>Celſus</hi> his Doctrine,<note place="margin">Origen. <hi>contra</hi> Celſum. <hi>lib.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> that they muſt be confided in, have Oblations and Prayers offered to propitiate them as their Laws require; and he calls them, the <hi>Peers</hi> of the Heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, chief Miniſters, and Officers of the High God.</q> And theſe were the Souls of Men, famous in their life time for ſome worthy Deeds, renowned and honoured after Death, as a middle and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58738:13"/>inferiour ſort of Gods;<note place="margin">Multi Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani Divos, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſque non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter veneran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quam De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um; nec video in multis quid ſit diſcrimen inter eorum opinionem de Sanctis, &amp; id quod Gentiles putabant de ſuis Diis. <hi>Lud. Viv. com. in Aug.</hi> de <hi>civit. Dei. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c. ult.</hi>
                  </note> and by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.20. which we tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate a <hi>Sacrificing to Devils,</hi> may as well, if not more properly, be meant, a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing to thoſe <hi>Daemons,</hi> to the Souls of brave Men ſurviving after Death, and ſuppoſed to be in a Capacity of doing good or evil to Men upon Earth.</p>
               <p>Let us now conſider whether the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> praying to <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, their burning Lights and Perfumes to them, preſenting them with Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Vows, do not exactly reſemble this <hi>Pagan Daemonolatry,</hi> and equal, if not exceed, the <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Superſtition</hi> of their <hi>Devotion</hi> herein.</p>
               <p>The Advocates for <hi>Popery</hi> indeed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that there are many great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in the Caſe; As,
<list>
                     <item>1. That the <hi>Heathens</hi> ador'd wicked Men either altogether unworthy of any, or worthy of diſgraceful Memory; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as their <hi>Church</hi> worſhips none, but ſuch as were of eminent Deſerts.</item>
                     <item>2. That whereas the <hi>Heathens</hi> invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked their <hi>Demi-Gods,</hi> as the immediate <hi>Authors</hi> and <hi>Beſtowers</hi> of particlar Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and good Things; they pray to the <hi>Saints</hi> only as <hi>Interceſſours,</hi> and more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent <hi>Supplicants</hi> to <hi>Almighty God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:58738:13"/>
                     <item>3. That they acknowledge one Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Superexcellent <hi>Being,</hi> and reſerve for him a Soveraign Honour as his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar; whereas the <hi>Heathens</hi> either did not own one Supream <hi>Being,</hi> or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the <hi>Devil</hi> as ſuch, and gave that ſingular Honour which was due to <hi>God,</hi> to the <hi>Creature.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>By ſuch diſtinctions as theſe they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to clear themſelves from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Participation with <hi>Heathens</hi> in this their <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe Pretences have been ſo well examined, and ſo fully confuted by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in every particular, that a brief reply to each will be ſufficient at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. As to the firſt, it is plain, that,<note place="margin">Bochart. Geogr. Sacr.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Many of thoſe whom the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> worſhipped were <hi>great</hi> and <hi>good</hi> Men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theoph. Gale,</hi> Court of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
                  </note> and it hath been noted by ſome learned Perſons that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve, Noah, Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet, Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> &amp;c. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeveral other Names. And if they worſhipped evil Men, it was upon miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, ſuch as our <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> with all their infallibilities, are not ſure to eſcape, and perhaps <hi>Thomas Becket</hi> and <hi>Father Garnet</hi> may be found at laſt not much better <hi>Saints</hi> then ſome of their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertuoſo's.</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:58738:14"/>However, the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the Service conſiſts, not in the qualification of the Creature to whom it is addreſſed; thoſe that <hi>worſhip</hi> good <hi>Angels,</hi> as well as thoſe that <hi>ſacrifice</hi> to <hi>Devils,</hi> are alike guilty of it, becauſe they give that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to the <hi>Creature,</hi> which is due only to the <hi>Creatour,</hi> as it is remarked by our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the 25 <hi>verſe</hi> of this 1 <hi>Chap.</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> It <hi>is a worſhipping</hi> or ſerving the <hi>Creature good</hi> or <hi>bad,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, beſides the <hi>Creator,</hi> who is bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> They pretend they only pray to <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> to pray with them, and for them to God, the only giver of all things, and ſo are clear of that <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> in making <hi>Demons,</hi> or the Souls of dead Men the Objects of their <hi>Adoration;</hi> and the Authors of their <hi>Bleſſings.</hi> But to this we anſwer theſe things: And,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It plainly appears by ſuch Practices of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> which the <hi>Popes</hi> themſelves have authorized, that their Invocation of a <hi>Saint</hi> doth not conſiſt in a meer <hi>Ora pro nobis;</hi> but in imploring particular Bleſſings and Relief, and ſome ſuch as is proper for none but God or Chriſt to give. As in their Prayers to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58738:14"/>St. <hi>Coſmas</hi> and St. <hi>Dominic,</hi> to keep them from all Diſeaſes, as well of Soul as of Body; that to St. <hi>Francis,</hi> to deliver them from the Bondage,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>More</hi>'s Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</note> and Slavery of <hi>Sin;</hi> that to St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> for Grace to bear the Croſs; and to St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Aſſaults of the <hi>Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I need not inſtance in their <hi>Hyperdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias,</hi> their exceſſive <hi>Idolatries,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Horae Sanctae Mariae ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum uſum <hi>Sarum.</hi>
                  </note> in the Worſhip of the Bleſſed <hi>Virgin;</hi> praying upon all occaſions in the ſame <hi>Forms</hi> to <hi>Her,</hi> as to <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Son;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalterium be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atae Mariae.</note> as appears in her <hi>Roſary,</hi> and elſewhere.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I anſwer, That if this Plea would acquit the <hi>Papists</hi> from <hi>Idolatry,</hi> the <hi>Heathens</hi> have as good right to it, as <hi>they.</hi> For it is plain, They looked upon their <hi>Demons</hi> or <hi>Dii Medioxumi,</hi> as <hi>Mediators,</hi> or Managers of their Affairs with the Supream God.<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>ad</hi> Rom. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> It was St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>'s Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that thoſe old <hi>Idolaters</hi> went to <hi>God</hi> by the <hi>Creatures;</hi> as we procure acceſs to an Earthly <hi>King,</hi> by ſome <hi>Court Favourite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They plead they own one <hi>Supream God,</hi> and make neither <hi>Saints</hi> nor <hi>Angels</hi> equal unto him, and worſhip him with a peculiar Honour incommunicable to any other: but the <hi>Heathens</hi> do not ſo, ſay they, as you have heard already.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:58738:15"/>
               <p>For anſwer to this, I ſay;</p>
               <p n="1">1. That admit the Romaniſts make no <hi>Saints</hi> equal, to God the <hi>Father,</hi> or to any <hi>Perſon</hi> in the <hi>Trinity,</hi> conſidered according to his <hi>Deity</hi> alone; yet it is a high degree of <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> to mention their Merits, <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Sufferings,</hi> as Motives for acceptance of their Prayers in our behalf; and to inveſt them with <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Royal Titles</hi> and <hi>Prerogatives,</hi> as he is our <hi>High Prieſt</hi> and only <hi>Agent</hi> in the holieſt <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of <hi>Heaven;</hi> ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pified by the <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> under the Law, who was to officiate alone in the <hi>Holy of Holies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3ly.</hi> Whereas they plead that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a peculiar Honour for God, which they call <hi>Latria,</hi> and give only <hi>Dulia,</hi> an inferior kind of Homage, a Service of Love and Reſpect to <hi>Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For anſwer hereunto, taking no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the preſumption and dangerous conſequence of making diſtinctions, where the <hi>Lawgiver</hi> hath made none: It is plain by all Circumſtances, that they give <hi>Religious Worſhip,</hi> however they call it, to <hi>Saints</hi> in their <hi>Invocations, burning Incenſe,</hi> and the like. Yea their own Word <hi>Dulia,</hi> notes Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as well as the other <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58738:15"/>
                  <hi>Duliam exhibebatis,</hi> you ſerved them,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.8.</note> which by Nature are not Gods. And it is obſerved that there is the ſame Word for them both, in the <hi>Hebrew.</hi> That, to be ſure, is <hi>Divine Worſhip</hi> which we give to any Perſon or Thing; as being endowed with thoſe <hi>Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties,</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> to know our Thoughts, to hear our Prayers at a diſtance, and to give relief in extraordinary and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known ways. This Worſhip the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> give to their <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels;</hi> and tho they call it <hi>Dulia,</hi> it is more than a civil Homage, the very ſame which the <hi>Scripture</hi> appropriates to God,<note place="margin">Arnob. <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 232.</note> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids us to give it to any other.</p>
               <p>And whereas they pretend further, that <hi>Sacrifice</hi> is the only external <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Latria.</hi> It is very apparent that <hi>Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> and <hi>Incenſe</hi> which they offer to their <hi>Saints,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">By Dr. <hi>Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth.</hi> Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet.</hi>
                  </note> were look'd on both by <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> as the more ſolemn and divine parts of Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It hath been cleared from all colour of rational Doubt and Diſpute, that the <hi>Heathens</hi> acknowledged one <hi>Supream Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Father of God's and Men.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 17.23.</note> And that he to whom they erected the <hi>Altar</hi> at <hi>Athens,</hi> was not the <hi>Devil,</hi> but the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58738:16"/>
                  <hi>God that made the World,</hi> and <hi>all things in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither did they equalize all with <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and uſe the ſame Form to him, and to their <hi>Demi-Gods</hi> and <hi>Heroicks;</hi> to whom they gave not an <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>ſovereign,</hi> but ſuch a kind of <hi>relative</hi> and <hi>ſubordinate Worſhip,</hi> as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs due to <hi>Saints.</hi> So that if one be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, the other cannot be condemned; and if one be condemned, the other can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be juſtified. Yea what ever was <hi>Idolatry</hi> in the <hi>Heathens,</hi> the ſame is ſo in us, with aggravation, if we commit it; becauſe they had not ſo expreſs a Declaration from <hi>God</hi> againſt all <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have.</p>
               <p>But to proceed; if I had time, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in all Particulars: The <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> might be further diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by ſhewing you how they imitate the <hi>Heathens,</hi> in praying to ſeveral <hi>Saints,</hi> in ſeveral Diſtempers and Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies. For beſides their Honour for <hi>Aeſculapius;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Orig. <hi>contra Celſ. l.</hi> 8. p 416.</note> 
                  <hi>Celſus</hi> tells us, that dividing Man's Body into 36 parts, each had its peculiar <hi>Demon,</hi> or <hi>Guardian-God,</hi> and he names divers of them. Yea the <hi>Popiſh Tutelar Saints,</hi> ſuch as St. <hi>Patrick, St. George,</hi> St. <hi>David,</hi> derive from the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>'s
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58738:16"/>and <hi>Heavenly Powers,</hi> which the <hi>Heathens</hi> believed did preſide over Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Cities, and Countries, according to that of <hi>Symachus; The Spirit of God which governeth this great World, hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed its Protectors to every City.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>According to the number of thy Cities,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judges 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo are thy Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that now upon the whole matter what was ſaid of the <hi>Idolatrous Iſraelites.</hi> They <hi>forſook</hi> the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>their Fathers, which brought them out of the Land of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and ſerved <hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſhtaroth,</hi> may juſtly be applied to theſe <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> They forſook the <hi>Lord</hi> that brought them out of the <hi>Spiritual Egypt,</hi> and worſhipped <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> and that with the <hi>Pagan</hi> Circumſtances of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated <hi>Altars, Images,</hi> and <hi>Temples.</hi> I may add to theſe, that the Papiſts Prayers to <hi>Saints</hi> as well as to <hi>God,</hi> conſiſt of vain Repetitions, witneſs the fifty <hi>Ave Maries</hi> in our <hi>Ladies Pſalter,</hi> witneſs the fifteen ſhort Ejaculations, in that which they call the <hi>Pſalter</hi> of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and their repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the name of Jeſus thirty times in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of them, which way of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you know is reproved by our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> in the Practice and Doctrines of the <hi>Heathens.</hi> The next thing we ſhall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:58738:17"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Their worſhiping of Images</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding the Doctrine of the <hi>Second Commandment,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſignalizing the Sottiſhneſs and Folly of the Practice; notwithſtanding the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral out-cry of the Fathers againſt it, for ſeveral <hi>Centuries,</hi> their forbidding ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the very making of <hi>Images,</hi> and diſallowing the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Painting</hi> for fear of this abuſe, and the Decrees of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Councils againſt it; yet this <hi>Church,</hi> which would ſeem to reject for <hi>heretical</hi> or impious whatſoever is not handed to them by the Fathers or <hi>Councils,</hi> hath thought good in her own <hi>Infallible Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and great Devotion, no doubt, to bow very low, and uſe more religious Ceremonies towards her <hi>Images,</hi> than the <hi>Heathens</hi> themſelves did to <hi>their's.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For was it not expreſly decreed in a Provincial <hi>Council,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Arch-Biſhop <hi>Uſher's</hi> Anſw. to the Jeſuites Challenge.</note> held at <hi>Oxford</hi> 1408, by <hi>Thomas Arundel</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> That it ſhould be commonly taught and preached by all, that the <hi>Croſs</hi> and <hi>Image</hi> of the Crucifix, and the reſt of the Images of the <hi>Saints,</hi> in memory and honour of them whom they figure, as alſo their <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques,</hi> ought to be worſhiped with <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions,</hi> bending of the Knee, bowings
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58738:17"/>of the Body, <hi>Incenſings, Kiſſings, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, Lighting of Candles,</hi> and Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea in the <hi>Roman Catechiſm,</hi> ſet out by the order of the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> is not the <hi>Pariſh Prieſt</hi> required to declare to his <hi>Pariſhioners,</hi> not only that it is lawful to have <hi>Images</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> but to give <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> to them? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for their Practice I need ſay lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, becauſe it hath been ſo fully demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by our moſt learned Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, and others of our <hi>Church:</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. That they ſet up <hi>Images</hi> in <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> over <hi>Altars,</hi> purpoſely to worſhip them.</item>
                     <item>2. That they conſecrate thoſe <hi>Images</hi> with Solemn Prayers for that purpoſe.</item>
                     <item>3. They uſe all the Rites of Worſhip to them, which the Heathen Idolaters uſed to their <hi>Images.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. They make ſolemn <hi>Proceſſions</hi> in honour of <hi>Images,</hi> carrying them with as much Pomp and Ceremony, as ever the <hi>Heathens</hi> did their <hi>Idols.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. That they cover their <hi>Altars</hi> and <hi>Images,</hi> and omit to burn <hi>Incenſe</hi> before them in the time of <hi>Lent,</hi> as the Heathens were wont to do at certain times.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:58738:18"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Dii quoque templorum foribus celentur apertis.<note place="margin">Ovid. Faſt. <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thure vacent Arae, ſtent<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſine igne foci.</l>
               </q>
               <p n="6">6. Their attributing Motion and Speech, and ſeveral miraculous Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the <hi>Images</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the bleſſed <hi>Virgin,</hi> hath even as much Truth and Reaſon in it,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>5.</hi> Hiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> as that which <hi>Livy</hi> and <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> report of the moving and talking of the <hi>Images</hi> of <hi>Fortune,</hi> and of <hi>Juno Moneta.</hi> I ſhall add no more upon this Head; not only becauſe ſo much hath been ſaid by our Proteſtant Writers, but becauſe their <hi>Caſander</hi> plainly confeſſeth,<note place="margin">Caſan. conſul.</note> that their Peoples Adoration paid to <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Statues,</hi> was equal to the worſt of the <hi>antient Heathens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Their Doctrine of Purgatory,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which hath no ground at all to ſtand upon in the Holy Scriptures, or as they have framed and modelled it in the Writings of the <hi>Antient Fathers;</hi> (if that will give it any Support or Credit) was taught of old in the <hi>Heathens</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58738:18"/>of their <hi>Acheruſia,</hi> and their Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Fire, which give a painful <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> of all the Spots and Stains of leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer <hi>Sins,</hi> and thereby prepare the Soul for Admiſſion into the <hi>Elyſian</hi> Fields,<note place="margin">Plato Phood.</note> the Regions of bleſſed Spirits. The next thing I ſhall take notice of, is;</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Their Prayers and Oblations for the Dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the <hi>Church Triumphant</hi> prays for this <hi>Militant,</hi> though they know not particular Mens Caſes (without a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Revelation) I make no doubt at all; and that <hi>Commemorations</hi> of the <hi>Dead,</hi> Prayers for them, and particular <hi>Interceſſions</hi> at the <hi>Celebration</hi> of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> practiſed in the Ancient Church, cannot be denyed.<note place="margin">Arch Biſhop <hi>Uſher's</hi> Anſw. to the Jeſuit. p. <hi>204. Voſſii Theſ. Theolog. 125.</hi>
                  </note> Yet it muſt be yielded withall, that theſe Prayers and Interceſſions had not any Relation to <hi>Purgatory,</hi> being offered in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half whom they ſuppoſed to be in a ſtate of Reſt and Happineſs; and they conſiſted partly of Praiſes, and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings for the bleſſed Eſtate, which, the Party deceaſed was entred upon; and partly of Supplications for the completion of their Bliſs at the day of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58738:19"/>Judgment, and the preſervation of their Memory upon Earth, for the good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Living. But there is no Warrant or Precedent at all in <hi>Church Antiquity,</hi> before the fourth <hi>Century,</hi> for the <hi>popiſh</hi> way of praying for the Dead; their <hi>Oblations</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices</hi> either for the mitigation of Purgatory-Pains, or deliverance out of them. Till then this was only the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>Heathen;</hi> As <hi>Arnobius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. adv. Gent.</note> in his Book againſt them, hath obſerved. It was their general Practice to pray for their departed Friends, and to offer Gifts, ſuch as Hony, Milk and Wine for them;<note place="margin">Ovid. Faſt. <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note> and the forecited Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther informs us, that they ſacrificed the Blood of certain living Creatures for the Purgation of the Souls of Men: And <hi>Plato</hi> in his 2 Book <hi>de Republica,</hi> tells us, that the dead are purged by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices;</hi> whereas the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſired to <hi>preach</hi> to his <hi>Romans,</hi> promiſes no relief at all to the Dead, from the Prayers, Sacrifices or Merits of the Living; forewarns us of no <hi>Wrath to come</hi> but what is <hi>eternal,</hi> no <hi>Fire</hi> but what is <hi>unquenchable,</hi> no <hi>Torments</hi> but thoſe of <hi>Hell,</hi> which are as immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and unmixed, as the Joys of <hi>Heaven;</hi> and makes the time of this Life, the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58738:19"/>only <hi>accepted time,</hi> the <hi>day of Salvation,</hi> exhorting us in <hi>this our day to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the things that belong to our Peace,</hi> to our future Happineſs, or Miſery; to <hi>make our Calling and Election ſure, and to work out our own Salvation,</hi> not truſting to others to do it for us, when the <hi>Night</hi> of Death <hi>comes</hi> upon <hi>our ſelves, wherein no Man can work.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:58738:20"/>
               <head>The Second Sermon.</head>
               <p>HItherto I have ſhewed, how little there is of <hi>Goſpel</hi> in the <hi>Romiſh Canonization</hi> of, or praying to <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> worſhipping of <hi>Images,</hi> Their Doctrine of <hi>Purgatory;</hi> and laſtly their <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Oblations</hi> for the dead: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o begin again where we left, tho we cannot take notice of all their Pleas and Defences, for their praying for the dead; yet we ſhall not conceal one which they rely much upon, and that is, what <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcen,</hi> if the Book <hi>de Defunctis</hi> be his, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ells us of a <hi>dead Man's Skull,</hi> that ſpake thus unto <hi>Macarius</hi> the <hi>Egyptian Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret; When thou doſt offer thy Prayers for the dead, then do we feel ſome little Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi> But this is no evidence againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of our <hi>Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this Brainleſs ſpeaking <hi>Skull,</hi> minds me to conſider in the next place;</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:58738:20"/>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Their great Devotion to Reliques.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Members, Blood, Bones; yea the Habits, or any of the Goods and Appurtenances of their Saints departed, to which they aſcribe as miraculous Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of ſeveral Natures, as the Speech of this <hi>Skull:</hi> only the rarity of this is, It was not the <hi>Skull</hi> of a <hi>Saint,</hi> but of a <hi>Heathen Prieſt;</hi> as the <hi>Greek Meneology</hi> will have it, and <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> takes it for granted.</p>
               <p>But if we conſider how idly and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhly they <hi>Romance,</hi> in extolling the wonder-working Power of ſome of their <hi>Reliques,</hi> we muſt conclude that the <hi>Confidence</hi> of the <hi>Reporters,</hi> and the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity</hi> of the <hi>Hearers,</hi> are the greateſt <hi>Miracles</hi> in the caſe, if their ſottiſh <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of them, be not ſtill more prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious. I will not preſent you with <hi>Heathen</hi> Precedents and Practices, to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate, but rather a little to excuſe the fondneſs of this <hi>Superſtition;</hi> which ſure they would be more aſhamed of, if it were not a little countenanced by ſuch Stories, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports concerning the Preſervation and devout Adoration of <hi>Theſeus</hi>'s <hi>Bones;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Vit. <hi>Theſ.</hi>
                  </note> and by what ſuch
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58738:21"/>a <hi>Sage-Philoſopher</hi> as <hi>Plato</hi> ſays, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Worſhip they gave to the very Shrines of their <hi>Hero</hi>'s, or deceaſed <hi>Worthies,</hi> and by that general Practice of the old <hi>Romans,</hi> not only of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, but reverencing their Bones and Aſhes,<note place="margin">Serv. <hi>in</hi> Virg.</note> as their Patrons and Defenders, <hi>tanquam Tutelares Patronos, Lares atque Penates.</hi> But I proceed to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of,</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>The Worſhip they give to the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Hoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I chooſe the rather to ſpeak of it juſt now, becauſe it may be, and hath been accounted, one <hi>Species</hi> of the <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> of <hi>Reliques;</hi> (The Body and Blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> being the <hi>Myſtical Reliques</hi> which he left us, as <hi>Monuments of his Death till he come.</hi>) If it may not more properly be reduced to <hi>Image-Worſhip,</hi> as being the <hi>Adoration</hi> of a <hi>Sign,</hi> or <hi>Symbol;</hi> which ſoever it be, I muſt confeſs,<note place="margin">Mr. Med.</note> with the learned <hi>Mede,</hi> it hath a ſtrain above the abomination of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who, tho they ſuppoſed ſome Preſence of their <hi>Demons</hi> in their <hi>Images,</hi> and <hi>Reliques,</hi> yet were they never ſo blockiſh, as to think their <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58738:21"/>and <hi>Reliques</hi> tranſubſtantiated into <hi>Demons.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caſter. Enchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid. Fiſher <hi>contra</hi> Oecolampa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium. <hi>l.</hi> 1.2.</note> Yea they themſelves acknowledg of their own Accord, that if the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> be not true, (which it cannot be, unleſs all the <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> of Mankind be falſe.) the <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> of the <hi>Heathens</hi> in worſhipping ſome Golden or Silver <hi>Statue,</hi> is more excuſable than theirs, in worſhipping a <hi>Bit of Bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>As for the Peoples receiving in one kind;</hi> (contrary to the continued Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Church for a thouſand years together) tho it cannot be ſuppoſed to be of an Original purely <hi>Heathen;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baron. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 26. <hi>p.</hi> 633. Bellarm. <hi>de</hi> Euchariſtia. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> yet for the Credit of its <hi>Antiquity, Baronius</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> do derive it from the Practice of the <hi>Manichees,</hi> their abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating of Wine, and their willingneſs to come to the <hi>Communion,</hi> (at leaſt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the Law and Cenſures of the <hi>Church</hi>) if they might receive the <hi>Bread</hi> without the <hi>Cup.</hi> Now from the <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters</hi> the Fathers give us of theſe <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheans,</hi> they were rather <hi>Infidels,</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> than <hi>Chriſtians;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertullian.</note> one of them calls them, <hi>alterius Divinitatis Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58738:22"/>
               <p n="9">9. Their locking up the <hi>Scriptures</hi> in an <hi>unknown Tongue;</hi> if it was not taken up in imitation of that <hi>Roman Law,</hi> which prohibited the common reading of the <hi>Sybilline Prophecy</hi>'s; yet it juſtifies it ſelf by the ſame Reaſons: Thoſe were not to be read, or publiſhed <hi>ſine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, &amp; Juſſu Senatus,</hi> without the Command and Licence of the <hi>Senate;</hi> As <hi>Tully,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Iſaac Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaub.</hi> Exercit. ad apparat. <hi>Baron.</hi> Annal. p. <hi>66.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Livy, Dio,</hi> inform us; and the Reaſon of their Concealment was, leſt Private and Factious Perſons ſhould under the countenance of their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, make any innovations in their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Ceremonies,</hi> or in the <hi>Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of their Country.</p>
               <p>I know, They are ready to defend this Practice, by a more worthy and warrantable Example,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Maimon.</hi> Praef. Par. <hi>11.</hi> more <hi>Nevochim. Hil. Jeſ.</hi> in <hi>Hottingeri,</hi> Theſau. Theol. p. <hi>78.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> The great <hi>Caution</hi> which the <hi>Jews</hi> uſed, in explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the more Difficult and <hi>Metaphyſical</hi> parts of their <hi>Religion;</hi> and particularly their prohibiting all, but wiſe and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſons, to ſtudy the Viſion of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi>'s <hi>Wheels,</hi> or any other abſtruſe, intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate part of <hi>Divinity;</hi> but their End in this, was rather to preſcribe a prudent Method to the People in reading the Scriptures, than to take them wholly out of their Hands. Let us next ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they can</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:58738:22"/>
               <p n="10">10. Say any thing more to the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for their <hi>Prayers</hi> in <hi>Latin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The learned <hi>Iſaac Caſaubon,</hi> in his Anſwer to the Epiſtle of Cardinal <hi>Peron</hi> (having noted, that King <hi>James</hi> read in a Book of a certain Popiſh <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prieſt, that Prayers in an unknown Tongue were more effectual and prevalent than thoſe which were underſtood) tells them plainly;<note place="margin">Quod inſulſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum deliri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ab Ethnicis primo excogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum.</note> 
                  <hi>This moſt ſenſleſs dotage was of Heathen Extraction.</hi> In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the <hi>Valentinian</hi> Hereticks uſed <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew,</hi> an unknown Language in their Worſhip, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that they might thereby raiſe the Wonder, if not the Devotion of the ſimple Vulgar; as <hi>Euſebius</hi> informs us.<note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>Hiſt.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Their placing ſuch Vertue and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy in the Sign of their Croſs, their Agnus Dei</hi>'s, &amp;c. which cannot ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally be attributed to them, ſeems pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel to the <hi>Bacchus Laureus,</hi> to the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Amulets</hi> among the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then;</hi> or to the <hi>Precatiunculae,</hi> or little Prayers, that the <hi>Turk</hi> carries about with him, as a Defenſative againſt all Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and Diabolical Aſſaults.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:58738:23"/>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>The Papiſts uſing Spittle in Baptiſm,</hi> ſeems to be derived from that <hi>Heatheniſh Rite</hi> the Satyriſt refers to.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Ecce Avia,<note place="margin">Perſius <hi>Satyr</hi> 2.</note> aut metuens Divum mater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera, cunis</l>
                  <l>Exemit puerum, frontem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> atque uda labella</l>
                  <l>Infami digito, &amp; luſtralibus ante ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livis</l>
                  <l>Expiat, —</l>
               </q>
               <p>And <hi>Pliny</hi> tells us at large,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>28.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Vertue they attributed to <hi>Spittle,</hi> with Alluſion whereunto <hi>Athanaſius</hi> calls the <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> Dotages of <hi>Priſcil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> and <hi>Montanus,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, old <hi>Womens Spittle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>The Ceremony of ſprinkling Holy Water was a Heatheniſh Rite, uſed in the Sanctifications and Luſtrations of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But River-Waters were thought to be leſs purgative, therefore thoſe only of the Sea, were uſed for the Expiation of greater Crimes,<note place="margin">Alexand. <hi>ab</hi> Alexan. dies. Gen.</note> 
                  <hi>Propter vim igneam magnopere purgationibus conſentaneam.</hi> For which Cauſe, queſtionleſs the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:58738:23"/>in the Compoſition of their <hi>Holy Water,</hi> make uſe of <hi>Salt,</hi> as one of the chief Ingredients, that it may come more near in nature to the Water of the <hi>Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not blame the <hi>Heathens</hi> much for their Waſhings and Cleanſings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory to their holy Services, nor the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s time, for waſhing their Hands at the <hi>Church-door</hi> before entrance; but I blame them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much for uſing them as expiatory to waſh away the Guilt, not only of other Crimes, but of Murder it ſelf; as <hi>Oreſtes</hi> did in <hi>Pauſanias</hi> after the killing of his Mother; and we condemn the ſame end of uſing it, much more in the <hi>Papiſts:</hi> For it is their's too;
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Haec Aqua benedicta deleat mihi delicta.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let this holy Bowle, cleanſe my Soul.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Burning Candles by dead Bodies,</hi> was innocent, and uſeful to them that watched by them, the night before the Interment; but when they thought the departed Souls benefitted thereby, the Ceremony was infected with <hi>Heatheniſh Superſtition,</hi> and was condemned by the Counſel of <hi>Eliberis.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58738:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Temperance</hi> and <hi>Mortification,</hi> are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by our <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and diſcreet Abſtinence and Faſting are very uſeful to call off our Minds from the blandiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Senſe, and ſerve many good ends of Religion: but this change of <hi>Diet</hi> which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> account <hi>faſting,</hi> reſembles a <hi>Superſtition,</hi> which the Jews were guilty of,<note place="margin">Declar. <hi>Eraſm.</hi> adverſus cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuras Theolog. <hi>Pariſ.</hi> p. <hi>41, 42.</hi>
                  </note> in their way of eating; as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> confeſſeth.</p>
               <p>Again, though the <hi>freedom of Mans Will,</hi> was the current Doctrine of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> for all the firſt Ages until St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>'s time; and God in Scripture with reſpect to his own Covenant, is ſaid to be juſt, as well as merciful in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring our labours of Love;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Smith's</hi> Select Diſcourſes, p. <hi>288. Hottinger.</hi> Theſaur. Philo. p. <hi>554.</hi>
                  </note> yet the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Opinion of <hi>Free-will,</hi> and the <hi>Meritoriouſneſs</hi> of their good Works, is as inexcuſable as the Notion of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt <hi>Phariſees</hi> about them.</p>
               <p>And both they, and the <hi>Talmudiſts,</hi> have the ſame Plea for their <hi>unwritten Traditions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I have not time to inſiſt upon more Particulars, either of <hi>Jewiſh</hi> or <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> Corruptions in the <hi>Roman Church;</hi> and it will be the leſs needful, becauſe I have already given you ſome of the moſt conſiderable Inſtances of their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58738:24"/>foul Relapſes and <hi>Apoſtacies,</hi> parallel with the greateſt Defections in the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Church,</hi> the <hi>Sin</hi> of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the Son of <hi>Nebat,</hi> their worſhipping the true <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Images, the Calves of Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and the way of <hi>Ahab</hi> their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of other <hi>Gods,</hi> beſides him, <hi>viz. Baalim-Demons,</hi> inferiour <hi>Gods,</hi> and <hi>Mediators,</hi> exactly accompliſhing that Prophecy of St. <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 11.2. that <hi>the ſecond, or outmoſt Court of the Temple,</hi> which is the ſecond ſtate of the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoſtacy of the latter Times.</note> (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> hath obſerved) <hi>toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the holy City, ſhould be trodden down by the Gentiles,</hi> (that is, overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the <hi>Gentiles Idolatry</hi>) <hi>fourty two Months.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that in the cloſe of this Argument, we will allow the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Religion,</hi> that in many parts of it, it was elder than the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or the Preachings of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf; and to their fierce charge of <hi>Noveliſm</hi> we may juſtly oppoſe that of the learned <hi>Scali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Scal. <hi>reſponſ. ad</hi> Serrar. Min.</note> 
                  <hi>Nos novatores non ſumus, ſed vos eſtis veteratores, Our Religion</hi> is not <hi>new,</hi> bearing the ſame Date with the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> but <hi>your's</hi> a little too <hi>old,</hi> profeſſed at <hi>Rome</hi> before ever St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or St. <hi>Peter preached there,</hi> in many
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58738:25"/>Parts ſymbolizing with that of your <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtened Anceſtors,</hi> the <hi>Gentile Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſome will ſay, Why ſhould we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject that, as a matter of Reproach to the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and to their <hi>Religion,</hi> which they glory in as a convincing Proof of its <hi>Truth,</hi> and Goodneſs, its agreeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the <hi>Law</hi> of Nature, and the beſt <hi>Reaſon</hi> of <hi>Mankind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For anſwer hereunto,</p>
               <p n="1">1. We muſt acknowledg, that <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity</hi> is the ſum or perfection of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Things were laudable, or paſſable in any <hi>Religion</hi> that hath been in the World.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That thoſe Practices in the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> which were not the Products of <hi>Superſtition,</hi> but Dictates of the <hi>Law</hi> of Nature we allow and embrace; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending all things that were ſolemn, decent, and comely in their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That as our <hi>Saviour</hi> was pleaſed to retain many of the received Practices among the <hi>Jews,</hi> only with ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Alterations as made them ſuit with the Doctrine, and nature of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:58738:25"/>So the Primitive <hi>Church,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſome Ceremonies, which the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> uſed, relating to the outward Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Decency of their Miniſteries, and Worſhip; ſuch as were the Habits of their <hi>Prieſts,</hi> their <hi>Faſts, Vigils, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtivals, Proceſſions,</hi> &amp;c. And no doubt it was well done at firſt to accommodate to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> ſuch cuſtoms of the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> as had nothing of <hi>Idolatry</hi> or <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition</hi> in them,<note place="margin">Pertinaci P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſmo m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt quum rei i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to um ſubla io potius irritaſſet. <hi>Beda.</hi>
                  </note> nothing of peculiar Oppoſition to the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> to procure thereby a more eaſie Entertainment to its Doctrines, and in ſome meaſure to abate the uſual Prejudices, which all new and ſtrange Inſtitutions meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Some Compliances which were uſeful, and neceſſary in the Infant-ſtate of the <hi>Church,</hi> might, and did become hurtful afterwards; and many great Men complained betimes, of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of <hi>Pagan</hi> Rites, even of ſuch, as were in their own nature indifferent;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> p. <hi>391.</hi>
                  </note> particularly becauſe the <hi>Gentiles</hi> uſed in the Services of their <hi>Idols,</hi> to ſit down immediately after they had prayed; <hi>Tertullian</hi> would not have the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do ſo.<note place="margin">De <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at.</hi> c. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. If there be any thing doctrinal in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58738:26"/>their <hi>Rites,</hi> the Obſervation of them will be an owning of their Religion, a joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chriſt</hi> with <hi>Belial,</hi> Light with Darkneſs; a corrupting and deflouring of the Purity, and Chaſtity of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. We have inſtanced for the moſt part, in Ceremonies of this nature; and have proved as fully, as well as we could in ſo little time and ſpace; that if there ever was any ſuch thing as <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> in the <hi>Heathen World;</hi> there is now too much of them in the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and the <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> ſo throughly infected with them, that in ſo general a Corruption, we cannot but contemplate, and lament that <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> or falling away of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> foretold by our <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. And by theſe Spiritual <hi>Adulteries,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude who is the <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> of the <hi>Formcations,</hi> and <hi>Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the Earth;</hi> who in our days, go a <hi>whoring after the Heathen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek 23.30.</note> and are <hi>polluted with their ldols.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore to apply this.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What we have heard of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> juſtifies our Separation from her; we depart no further from her, than ſhe hath done from <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:58738:26"/>and renounce only the <hi>Heatheniſm</hi> and other foreign Corruptions, which ſhe hath mixed with the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We do not voluntarily make a <hi>Schiſm</hi> upon the account of a ſtinted <hi>Liturgy,</hi> a few <hi>indifferent Ceremonies,</hi> or ſome little Defects, and Diſorders in the lower Forms of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Polity;</hi> but are forced to ſeparate from ſuch <hi>Idolatries</hi> and <hi>Superſtitions,</hi> as are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether inconſiſtent with the Doctrine, and Worſhip of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It concerns thoſe that would not partake of the Sins of <hi>Rome,</hi> the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Babylon,</hi> and receive of her <hi>Plagues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 18.4.</note> to <hi>come</hi> out of <hi>her,</hi> according to our <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle's</hi> Advice, to come out <hi>from among them,</hi> to be <hi>ſeparate,</hi> and <hi>not to touch the unclean Thing.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor 6.17.</note> For what <hi>Concord</hi> hath <hi>Chriſt</hi> with <hi>Belial,</hi> or the <hi>Temple of God, with Idols?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Let us highly magnifie the unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and diſtinguiſhing Goodneſs of God, for delivering us from thoſe <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> and Abominable <hi>Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> wherewith for ſome time the whole <hi>Church,</hi> in a manner, was, and ſtill a great part of it is, overſpread, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring to us the clear, and pure Light
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58738:27"/>of his <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and let us moſt humbly and heartily pray for the continuance of this Bleſſing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou haſt brought up a Vine out of</hi> Egypt, <hi>thou haſt caſt out the Heathen and planted it; let not the Wild Boar out of the Wood root it up, nor the Wild Beaſt of the Field devour it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, it concerns us to bleſs God for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering us from the Cruelties of the <hi>'Papiſts,</hi> wherein they alſo <hi>Gentilize</hi> (as I ſhould have ſhewed if I had had time) and particularly from the moſt mercileſs Deſign of this day; a Deſign which at once outwitted the Malice of paſt, and the Imitation of future <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies,</hi> and which if it had taken ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, would not only have ſatisfied the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Spirit of the worſt of <hi>Men,</hi> but (if any thing would) the Hatred, Enmity, and Revenge, of the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf, who was a <hi>Murderer from the beginning. Curſed be their Anger, for it was ſierce;</hi> and <hi>their Wrath, for it was cruel;</hi> But for ever bleſſed be God, <hi>who bringeth the Counſel of the Heathen to naught.</hi> And bleſſed <hi>is the Nation whoſe God is the Lord, and the People whom he hath choſen for his own Inheritance. We thy People, and Sheep of thy Paſture will
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58738:27"/>give thee Thanks for ever, we will ſhew forth thy Praiſe to all Generations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Let us endeavour to conſirm our ſelves by theſe Conſiderations in the true Faith, which we profeſs, and in a ſtedfaſt Obedience to the pure <hi>Goſpel</hi> of our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</hi> Not <hi>learning the way of the Heathen;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 10.2.</note> 
                  <hi>not giving heed to ſeducing Spirits and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Demons;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4 1.</note> 
                  <hi>To ſuch as ſpeak Lies in Hypocriſie. forbidding to marry, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding to abſtain from Meats.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whatever there is of <hi>Goſpel</hi> and true <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> we have it already; and what is more, either purely of their own Invention, or borrowed from the <hi>Heathens, who have changed the Truth of God into a Lie,</hi> I hope we ſhall be content to want. We hold the <hi>Foundation Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and reject none of the <hi>Gold, Silver,</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Stones,</hi> which they built upon it, but the ſuperadditions of Hay and Stubble; ſuch Doctrines and Practices of theirs, as are not to be found in <hi>Scripture,</hi> nor in the <hi>Creeds, Homilies,</hi> and <hi>Canons</hi> of the Primitive <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding their great boaſts of <hi>Antiquity</hi> (which prevail much where they are believed) it is a plain caſe, that the <hi>Popery</hi> of their <hi>Religion</hi> if not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58738:28"/>new in it ſelf, is new in the <hi>Church,</hi> never profeſſed by any <hi>Chriſtians</hi> for the firſt three hundred Years, and as to the groſſer parts of it, not known in the <hi>Church,</hi> until ſeveral Ages after.</p>
               <p>We may patiently hear them upbraid us with <hi>Singularity,</hi> and <hi>Innovation,</hi> when we are aſſured our Doctrines are as old, and as <hi>univerſal</hi> as our <hi>Saviour's Goſpel;</hi> and we may allow them to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in any thing older and more <hi>Catholick</hi> than that. Their Religion will not appear to us more ſacred and venerable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe much of its Attire, many of its Rites and Ceremonies, are more antique than ours; and becauſe it is adorned in thoſe <hi>Faſhions of the World, thoſe Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Gentiles,</hi> which as they were before <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> ſo were to paſs away at its Appearance, and where they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, or rather have been reaſſumed, are the Blemiſh, and Diſgrace, if not the Diſeaſe, and Leproſie, of that moſt excellent Inſtitution.</p>
               <p>But on the contrary, I hope we ſhall be more fervent, more ſettled and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in our Affection to, and Zeal for our own <hi>Religion,</hi> when we conſider that it is ſound and pure <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> the only <hi>Catholick Religion,</hi> which hath
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58738:28"/>in it all that is truly good of all other <hi>Religions,</hi> without their Adulterations and Debaſements. It is a Religion which doth not allow us to <hi>give Gods Glory to another,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 42.8.</note> nor <hi>his Praiſe to graven Images.</hi> It admits neither <hi>Saints</hi> nor <hi>Angels</hi> to ſhare in <hi>God</hi>'s Worſhip, nor owns any other <hi>Mediatours,</hi> but his Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It is a Religion which enjoyns none, but <hi>Reaſonable Services,</hi> which allows us to <hi>ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> and prove all things; not exacting an <hi>Implicite Faith,</hi> or <hi>Blind Obedience.</hi> It gives us to underſtand what God ſaith to us, and what we pray for to him, in the uſe of an <hi>Engliſh Bible</hi> and <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy.</hi> It is a Religion which makes no more Sacraments, than our Saviour did, but gives us them intire. In a word, it is a Religion which is pure, and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, which diſpenſeth with no Duties of <hi>Piety, Righteouſneſs,</hi> or <hi>Charity;</hi> which teacheth Obedience to Governours, and abhors <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Treaſon,</hi> as one of the worſt things in <hi>Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Methinks no worldly Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, no Hopes or Fears ſhould cauſe us to waver in, much leſs to depart from, a <hi>Religion,</hi> ſo purely <hi>Chriſtian</hi> as this; So <hi>Profitable unto all things</hi> in our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58738:29"/>and private Capacities, maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Peace, and Property, the Power of Soveraigns, and Rights of Subjects; <hi>Giving to God the things that are Gods, and to Ceſar thoſe that are his,</hi> no way oppreſſing the meaneſt of the People in their civil Concerns, and moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually promoting the ſpiritual Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, and Happineſs of all Men; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, I ſay, we ſhould not eaſily be perſwaded out of ſuch a Religion, at leaſt not to change it for that which we have heard deſcribed, one depraved with the moſt fond <hi>Superſtitions</hi> and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous</hi> Rites of <hi>Gentiliſm;</hi> nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed for any other, which under the pretence of greater Purity, doth real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comply with, and advance the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of this. What true Good can we propound to our ſelves by ſuch an Exchange? Let us therefore reſolve to continue, and fix where we are, Saying with thoſe in another Caſe; <hi>Whither ſhall we go, thou haſt the words of Eternal Life?</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>
                  <hi>The End of the ſecond</hi> Sermon.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermons">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:58738:29"/>
            <head>THE GOSPEL Preached to them that are At <hi>ROME</hi> Alſo. IN TWO SERMONS, On the <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1680.</head>
            <div n="3" type="sermon">
               <head>The Third Sermon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ROM. 1.15.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>So as much as in me is, I am ready to preach the Goſpel to you that are at <hi>Rome</hi> alſo.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HItherto I have been diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Anti-Chriſtian</hi> Errors of profeſſed <hi>Papiſts,</hi> in order to your Confirmation and Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, rather than (what I yet moſt heartily deſire) their Conviction and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58738:30"/>Recovery, becauſe I know not whether this Diſcourſe may reach any of them.</p>
               <p>There are another ſort of Men who think themſelves far enough from <hi>Rome,</hi> or at leaſt would have us think them ſo; who upon a true enquiry will be found to be their <hi>Alſo.</hi> I mean theſe among our ſelves, who whilſt they loudly proteſt againſt the <hi>Heatheniſh Superſtitions,</hi> and <hi>Idolatries</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> do yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine with them, yea with the worſt of them, the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> in many of their Principles and Practices, no leſs <hi>unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian;</hi> and ſtrengthen the Hands and Hearts of thoſe our implacable Enemies, by dividing the Body, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently waſting the Force of our <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would not at this time eſpecially, diſcourage the Zeal of any well meaning <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> by aggravating the Errors and Irregularities of it; but ſure they muſt needs be very <hi>ſhallow Headed,</hi> if they are indeed <hi>true Hearted,</hi> and well meaning <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who think in theſe Days to ſerve their Cauſe, to bring Honour and Security to their Religion, by breaking the Orders and Unity of our <hi>Church,</hi> by mutinying againſt their
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58738:30"/>Leaders, and drawing off into Parties, and Factions, from the main of their Strength, if not turning their Weapons upon, and making at thoſe as their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who have been at leaſt their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, if not their <hi>Champions,</hi> in the common Quarrel. In order to the tempering and directing of theſe Men's Zeal, I would in the Spirit of Meekneſs, the Spirit of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> propound theſe things to their ſober Thoughts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That however they may value themſelves upon their Courage and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs, yet they will never be crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with due Praiſe, nor have any juſt cauſe to triumph in their Victories, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they ſtrive lawfully,</hi> acting within the compaſs of their own Calling, and Quality, not violently invading other Men's Offices, but patiently waiting for God's Bleſſing upon the faithful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their own.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that are otherwiſe perſuaded, are in that Particular, <hi>at Rome alſo.</hi> Where we all know it is taught and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, as ſound Doctrine; that a very good End doth Legitimate and Sanctify the worſt Means that can be uſed for at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:58738:31"/>
               <p n="2">2. If the Power, Policies, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of our Enemies be at this time very dreadful, as indeed they are, I would adviſe them to conſider; whether the <hi>Proteſtant Cauſe</hi> is like to gain any thing, by their repreſenting their Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and Strength, to be more ſtill, and more terrible than really it is: I mean, by reducing every thing to <hi>Popery,</hi> which ſuits not their ſingular Models, and Forms of Government and Worſhip.</p>
               <p>Sure if the <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Sons</hi> in this our <hi>National Church,</hi> are for the moſt part <hi>Popiſhly affected,</hi> as too many of them, do moſt diſingenuouſly, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed diſhoneſtly ſuggeſt, the very Heart of our Religion would fail for want of its wonted and proper Succours and Support.</p>
               <p>How formidable would the Intereſt of <hi>Rome</hi> then be, if there were none but diſagreeing, and ſcattered Forces to oppoſe it?</p>
               <p>His <hi>Majeſty</hi> in his <hi>Declaration</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Affairs,</hi> 1660. was pleaſed to ſignify, <hi>That in his Converſe with the moſt Learned of the Reformed Churches abroad; they did always with great Submiſſion, and Reverence, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and magnify the Eſtabliſhed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58738:31"/>of the</hi> Church of England, <hi>and the great Countenance and Shelter the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion received by it, before the late unhappy Times; and that, many of them have with great Ingenuity and Sorrow con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that they were too eaſily miſled by Miſinformations and Prejudice into ſome Diſeſteem of it; as if it had too much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>whereas they now acknowledg it to be the beſt Fence God hath raiſed againſt Popery in the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe that go about to pull down this <hi>Bulwark,</hi> or fire this Caſtle, for fear it ſhould ſurrender to the Enemy; I would deſire them to think in time, how naked and defenceleſs they will leave the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do not really expoſe what they pretend to preſerve, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the Building of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> with every Stone they take from <hi>Ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. I would deſire the Beginners of the <hi>Separation,</hi> to reflect ſeriouſly upon the Iſſues of their former Practices. I mean, not only the ſhedding of ſo much Blood, the Blood of their Equals, their Nobles, their <hi>King himſelf;</hi> in purſuit of the Quarrel they began, but the great
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58738:32"/>occaſion they gave thereby (tho I hope ſome of them unwittingly) of Triumph to our <hi>Popiſh Adverſaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We know very well how ready they were to throw back upon our <hi>Religion,</hi> that heavy Charge of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> which we had ſo juſtly laid upon <hi>theirs;</hi> and by noting the irregular Practices of ſuch Zealous Profeſſors, how much they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to depretiate and beat down the eſteem of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> where it was moſt valued, to raiſe ſome Men's Averſions, to an abhorrence of it, and to confirm and heighten the diſlike of others, into the utmoſt degree of Contempt. The generality of weak, but honeſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who obſerved things in their naked and proper Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances, without the colourings of either ſide, the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Excuſes, or the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Aggravations, were put into great Doubts, and waverings of Mind, which part they ſhould adhere to, the <hi>Idolatrous Papist,</hi> or the <hi>Sacrilegious Proteſtant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Learned and truly Moderate Man <hi>Monſieur Amyrant,</hi> in the Epiſtle Dedicatory of his Paraphraſe upon the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> to <hi>His Majeſty</hi> that now is, gives him to underſtand; how much
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58738:32"/>the Proceedings of the <hi>Puritans</hi> here, were objected to him by a great Peer of <hi>France,</hi> in way of Reproach to the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> as if it moved to Sedition, and Rebellion; and were a perfect Enemy to <hi>Monarchical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the bleſſed <hi>Martyr</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Father;</hi> fearing leſt the Scandal of the late Troubles might be objected to his <hi>Son,</hi> againſt our eſtabliſhed <hi>Religion:</hi> He furniſheth him with this Anſwer. <q rend="margQuotes">That ſcarce any one that hath been a Beginner or Proſecutor of the late War againſt the Church, the Laws, and Himſelf, either was, or is a true Lover, Embracer or Practicer of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion eſtabliſhed in <hi>England,</hi> which neither gives ſuch Rules, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before ſet ſuch Examples.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I would deſire thoſe yet ſurviving, who did begin, or carry on that unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py War, after ſo fair a time of cooling, to conſider calmly what it ended in, how much our <hi>Religion</hi> loſt, and how much <hi>Popery</hi> gained by it; and that they would have a very jealous Eye upon every Diſcontent, and turbulent Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which tends the ſame way again, and not juſtify thoſe Actions now, which
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58738:33"/>ſometimes ſince, in their own Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, could not be pardoned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a great <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea on this day of our ſorrowful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, upon the moſt execrable Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ever the Sun ſaw; (for that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Saviour the Sun would not look upon) How much doth it concern us to bewail, not only that laſt, and moſt daring Villany; but all the cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Complaints, the Factions, and the Fightings, that made way for it: En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring by all good Conſiderations to encreaſe our Abhorrence, and Dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of ſo black a Crime; and by our peaceable Behaviour, and chearful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Scepter we live under, to ſecure our ſelves from the leaſt touch, and ſtain of any ſuch Guilt for the time to come.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I would adviſe our diſſenting Brethren to conſider, how far a great part of them have <hi>advanced</hi> towards <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſymbolized with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> not only in their own frequent Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſolemn Oaths; thoſe of <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> the <hi>Covenant</hi> of their own framing and impoſing, but in their ſpecious offers of a Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58738:33"/>for our <hi>Royal Martyrs Goronation-Oath,</hi> relating to the maintenance of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> with the Legal Rites, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Priviledges of the <hi>Clergy;</hi> But alſo in their Imperious Solicitations of him to give up that great Truſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his declared Judgment and Conſcience, and that notwithſtanding his ſignal readineſs to comply with them in any thing where he lawfully might.</p>
               <p>God knows, I am very unwilling, even upon this day, to look back upon any thing of this nature, which I might honeſtly over-look.</p>
               <p>And indeed my own Circumſtances in the <hi>Church,</hi> and the preſent temper of the Nation is ſuch, that I cannot be ſuppoſed in an equal Judgment, to be biaſſed to any Partiality in defence of our preſent Conſtitution, either againſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> or any other Aggreſſors or, Underminers of it; and however I may be cenſured by any ſort of Men for the ſeeming Imprudence or unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of ſuch plain dealing; I really deſign nothing elſe but the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſcharge of a neceſſary Duty, even in this Advice, and I pray God remove all prejudicate Opinions.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:58738:34"/>
               <p>But if they will not be perſwaded to look back upon what is paſt, and think it hard to be put upon doing ſo, after an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Pardon</hi> and <hi>Indemnity:</hi> I would deſire them to conſider in the fifth place:</p>
               <p n="5">5. What good Effect they can ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally promiſe themſelves, of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Separation; whether the breaking of Unity, and Order at this time, is not the great Advantage which out Enemies deſire, and by all means deſign, inſomuch that now, to be ſure, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is not <hi>with us,</hi> is <hi>againſt us;</hi> they that ſeparate from us, much more they that ſtrive, and contend with us though about leſſer matters, are againſt us in the main.</p>
               <p>It is obſervable, in what manner the Contention between <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Herdſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and <hi>Lot</hi>'s is related.<note place="margin">Gen. 13.7.</note> 
                  <hi>And there was a Strife between</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Herdſmen, and the Herdſmen of</hi> Lot's <hi>Cattel;</hi> and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate the unſeaſonableneſs of the Strife, it follows immediatly; <hi>And the</hi> Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anite, <hi>and the</hi> Perizzite <hi>dwelt in the Land:</hi> It is ſet down as an aggravation of their Sin and Folly, that they ſhould fall out and quarrel, while the <hi>Heathens</hi> were ſo near them, and thereby expoſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58738:34"/>their <hi>Religion</hi> to Contempt; and, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to our own Caſe, doubtleſs it is no leſs Unwiſe, than Unchriſtian, for us to divide and quarrel among our ſelves, now the <hi>Canaanite</hi> and the <hi>Perizzite</hi> dwell in the Land, now the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> thoſe <hi>Gentilizing Chriſtians,</hi> are among us not only as Lookers on, but as buſie Promoters of our Diſſentions, and evil Deſigns thereupon.</p>
               <p>Our Apoſtle, the Doctor of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> (the propriety of whoſe Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion drew him to have a ſpecial care of thoſe without) ſaith, if a <hi>Heathen come in and hear you ſpeak with ſeveral Tongues,</hi> will he not ſay that you are mad? you will not only diſgrace your ſelves, but by your Diviſions harden him in his Superſtition.</p>
               <p>One of the ſhrowdeſt Enemies of Chriſtianity that ever appeared in the World, was <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> and we read in <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus lib.</hi> 22. that he could not invent any more effectual way, to ruine what he ſo much hated, than by encouraging all the Profeſſors of it in their diſtinct forms and ways of Opinion and Worſhip. and we know the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have learned this Wiſdom from that <hi>Heathen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:58738:35"/>to promote <hi>Diviſion,</hi> and <hi>Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of ſeveral <hi>Sects;</hi> that when they could do nothing againſt the whole, one part might deſtroy another. And can we think of upholding <hi>the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion,</hi> by the very ſame Arts and Methods which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have all along uſed to pull it down, and which the <hi>Pagans</hi> have uſed to extirpate <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelf; Therefore ſurely, thoſe who have ſeparated from us upon little Differences, if they are what they pretend to be, <hi>'Proteſtants</hi> indeed, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſee the greateſt Reaſon imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, to come in with ſpeed, and to joyn cordially and cloſly, in helping to repair thoſe Breaches in the Chucrh, (which they themſelves firſt made) at which ſwarms of <hi>Sectaries</hi> have entred in among us, and too many others, have gone out into the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> ſurely it concerns them now, not only in Duty, but in Policy and Intereſt, to go as far in Conformity, to come as near us, as poſſibly they can, and to let their Followers know, what they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of themſelves, that neither our <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> or <hi>Liturgy,</hi> are <hi>Popiſh,</hi> but far more odious to thoſe at <hi>Rome,</hi> than to any others, and that there is nothing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58738:35"/>required of <hi>Lay-Men</hi> in the way of Declaration, or Subſcription, which they of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> could not freely ſubmit to.</p>
               <p>That ſuch as Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> (whom I name for the Eminency and Influence of his Example) now there is more need of <hi>a Cure of Church-Diviſions,</hi> than when he wrote his Book with that Title, would ſpeak out again, and tell the World as he doth in the Preface of his Defence of that Book. <q rend="margQuotes">That our Diviſion gratifieth the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and greatly hazardeth the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and that more than moſt of the Diſſenters ſeem to believe, or to regard. And as in another place, that <hi>Popery</hi> will get ſo great an Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by the Separation, as may ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard us all, and we may loſe that which the ſeveral Parties do contend about.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I could wiſh they would reflect upon what was long ſince written by their own Mr. <hi>Shepherd</hi> of new <hi>England.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Parable of the Virgins, <hi>p. 8.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That it is the Jeſuites Plot, to ſubdue by private Diviſions, whom they cannot conquer by open force. It was moſt pleaſing to Satan to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to caſt himſelf down
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58738:36"/>headlong from the <hi>Temple,</hi> rather than to fling him down himſelf. 'Tis the delight of <hi>Hell</hi> to ſet, and ſee Churches at variance among themſelves <hi>&amp;c.</hi>— It is a wonderful thing, to ſee what a a ſmall occaſion of Offence will do, a Word, a Geſture, a Garment, a matter of Indifferency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> —</q>
               </p>
               <p>That they would conſider, and lay to heart, what that once great Man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, Mr. <hi>Philip Nye,</hi> wrote a little before his Death, concerning the <hi>Lawfulneſs of hearing the Conforming Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> particularly that place towards the Concluſion, where he wonders, <q rend="margQuotes">How the differing Parties came to be ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed in thinking it unlawful to hear us preach, and that he is perſwaded that it is one conſtant Deſign of Satan in the variety of ways of Religion, he hath ſet on Foot by <hi>Jeſuites</hi> among us.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That they would conſider the laſt, and dying Apprehenſions, of their late Champion Dr. <hi>Lewis Du Moulin,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what himſelf had formerly, and not long ſince written and ſpoken with a great deal of Paſſion and Virulency, for the widening of our Breaches, the defaming of our Church, and the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifying
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58738:36"/>of ſome of the moſt eminent and worthy Perſons therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> To ſave my ſelf and others any further Trouble, or Travail in this Argument; I would earneſtly commend to their ſober and impartial reading, our great Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet</hi>'s late and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Book of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Separation.</hi> And then I hope, we ſhall no longer by our imprudent and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Diviſions, hold open a Door, as it were for <hi>Popery</hi> to enter in upon us, nor by declaring againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> upon the diſtinct Intereſts of our ſingular Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, verify that of <hi>Tacitus</hi> in another Caſe; <hi>Dum ſinguli pugnabant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Vitâ <hi>Agric.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi vincebantur,</hi> when they broke their Ranks, and would fight ſingle, all were eaſily overcome.</p>
               <p>But if none of theſe Conſiderations, or any other, will temper the obſtinacy of our Diſſenters, and perſuade them to Peace and Union; I muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, notwithſtanding all their Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the contrary, and their vehement Outcries againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> that they are at <hi>Rome alſo.</hi> And I am the more confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this, becauſe <q rend="margQuotes">Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf, was once perſuaded that all the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments elſe in <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> and all other
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58738:37"/>Books that ever were written, have not done ſo much to make <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> as the multitude of Sects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But there are another ſort of Men, who are at <hi>Rome alſo.</hi> I mean, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſtical and Profane, the careleſs, and looſe Livers among our ſelves; for as my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> hath well obſerved.<note place="margin">Controverſies of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> p. <hi>168.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">There is a double Policy of the Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Enemy, either by counterfeit Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Life, to eſtabliſh and authorize Errors, or by corruption of Manners, to diſcredit and draw into queſtion, Truth and things lawful.</q>
               </p>
               <p>No <hi>Pagan</hi> Blaſphemies, or <hi>Popiſh</hi> U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpations, are ſo offenſive to God, or injurious to his Church, as the ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous miſcarriages of his pretended Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: Our greateſt Fear and Danger, <hi>Beloved,</hi> is from our ſelves: Our <hi>Sins,</hi> are our worſt Enemies, and, if not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by us, will ſoon betray and ruine us, and our <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Cauſe, without any other Plots, and Conſpiracies. When we conſider what it was, that bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted thoſe flouriſhing <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Epheſus, Sardis, Laodicea;</hi> we cannot eſcape ſome fearful abodes, of the like effects, of our decay of <hi>Love,</hi> our <hi>Hypocritical
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58738:37"/>Profeſſion,</hi> our <hi>Lukewarmneſs,</hi> and great indifferency in the moſt material Parts and Acts of our Religion.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (and God grant we may be truly ſenſible of it) hath ſuffered much, and is ſtill like to ſuffer more by her own Children. And that is verified in her, which was once ſaid of <hi>Julius Caeſar, Plures illum amici confoderunt quam inimici.</hi> She hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived more Wounds from her Friends, than from her Enemies.</p>
               <q>Victa eſt non aegre proditione ſua.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ovid.</hi> de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinnâ.</note>
               </q>
               <p>How many among us are there that profeſs little, or no regard at all to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or profeſs that regard for the temporal Conveniencies that attend it? And how many are falſe and hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal in their Profeſſion, reſting in meer Shadows, and external Formalities? moſt unreaſonably concluding that all is well with them, becauſe the Lines are fallen to them, in ſo pleaſant a place as a purged <hi>Church,</hi> and that themſelves need <hi>Reformation</hi> the leſs, becauſe that is <hi>reformed?</hi> What is this, but as one ſpeaks? <q rend="margQuotes">To run round in a Circle, and meet the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> where we
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58738:38"/>left her?</q> What is this, but to ſpeak her very Language, that to be in this <hi>Ark,</hi> this <hi>Church,</hi> is to be ſafe?</p>
               <p>Behold, we are called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and reſt in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and make our Boaſts of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Purity of his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Worſhip among us!</p>
               <p>But believe it, it is not the Name of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> or <hi>Reformed,</hi> no nor the Name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf that will ſave us, or our Religion; if by our wicked Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, we cauſe that Name, that <hi>worthy Name,</hi> (as St. <hi>James</hi> calleth it) to be <hi>evil ſpoken of among the Gentiles,</hi> our <hi>Popiſh</hi> or our <hi>Phanatical</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p>It is our <hi>walking in this Holy Name;</hi> our living up to the Principles of our <hi>Saviour's Goſpel,</hi> and our improving the Means of Grace to a more perfect Degree of Holineſs, than any have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto in the Strength of Nature, or of their own artificial Inventions, that will make <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> truly glorious in the Eyes of <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens;</hi> Our <hi>Proteſtant Chriſtianity</hi> to out-ſhine the <hi>Viſibility</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and our <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to flouriſh, and be honourably eſteemed, among all her Siſters of the <hi>Reformation.</hi> Our Skill
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58738:38"/>in Controverſies, will not do us the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, nor gain us the Reputation, that the Simplicity of our Manners, the Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Practices will; This is that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> ſtiles it, the moſt uncontroulable, or irreſiſtable, if we may not ſay infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Proof, and Conviction of the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Religion in the Judgment of moſt Examiners.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore conclude this Head of my Diſcourſe, with an earneſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to Holineſs of Life: That our ways may be <hi>upright as among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and our well-doing ſuch,</hi> and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary, as may put <hi>to ſilence the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of fooliſh</hi> and captious <hi>Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a ſhame to our Religion, that we ſhould go to <hi>Rome</hi> for Examples of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, or ſeek <hi>Chriſt in the ſecret Chambers;</hi> that we ſhould learn Piety from <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> or ſtrictneſs of Life from the <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Government;</hi> yet even among them may be found ſome Inſtances of Mortification, and Zeal, which may ſerve at leaſt for our Reproach, if not for our Imitation. The voluntary Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> their Mid-night
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58738:39"/>Devotions, frequent Faſtings, painful Pilgrimages, and Pennances, may ſerve to put us in mind of our Saviour's wholeſome Precepts of Self-denial, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly-mindedneſs, devout Prayer, and diſcreet Abſtinence; and the Zeal of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Sectaries,</hi> in ſome parts of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may condemn our general Coldneſs, or Indifferency in the whole.</p>
               <p>But if we can learn no good from them, let us be very careful, leſt we har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den them in evil, and confirm them in their Erroneous Opinions, by our vitious Practices.</p>
               <p>When we have diſarmed them of their defenſive Weapons, and left them no rational Plea, nor Excuſe, for their Schiſm, and Sedition; Let us not put into their Hands, a Sword of Offence, and expoſe our ſelves to the Mercy of their Cenſures (which is cruel enough) by any Irregularities of another nature. And becauſe many among us at this time, appear more zealous for the Intereſt of their <hi>Religion,</hi> than that of their <hi>Souls,</hi> leſs mindful of the great Duties of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> in their own Converſations, than thoſe of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcovering, oppoſing, and puniſhing, the heretical and traiterous Deſigners
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58738:39"/>againſt our <hi>Proteſtant Church,</hi> and ſeem more to fear the <hi>Popiſh Conſpiracies,</hi> than any of the <hi>Devil's</hi> Wiles and Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems; I would deſire it might be well conſidered that a holy, good Life is as neceſſary to uphold our <hi>Religion,</hi> as to ſave our <hi>Souls.</hi> Nothing like this, as hath been intimated already to break the Courage, and baffle the Attempts of our <hi>Romiſh</hi> Adverſaries, or to reclaim and bring home other Diſſenters into our Communion.</p>
               <p>Nothing ſo like to fix and ſettle them in their Errors and Seditions, as our looſe and vain Converſations; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed at this time, we ought to be more then ordinarily circumſpect, now ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny evil Eyes are upon us, <hi>watching for our haltings,</hi> and ſo many Mouths ready opened to aggravate our leaſt Miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages; wherefore we could never more ſeaſonably apply to our ſelves, that of good <hi>Nehemiah, Ought we not to walk in the Fear of our God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. 5.9.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the Heathen, our Enemies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Among all the Motives and Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſives to Holineſs, me-thinks this ſhould not be the leaſt powerful, that it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if any thing, to gain thoſe that diſſent from us, to convince the more ſober and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58738:40"/>ingenuous, that we are in the right way of Worſhip; and to remove all Stones of Offence out of the Path, either of the tender, or peeviſh.</p>
               <p>An eminent Example of,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Edward Fowler</hi> in his deſign of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. <hi>p. 304.</hi>
                  </note> and a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Advocate for Holineſs hath well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, <q rend="margQuotes">That meer pretences to great <hi>Sanctity,</hi> do ſtrangely make <hi>Proſelites</hi> to ſeveral Forms, that have nothing beſides to ſet them off, and commend them: And as for obſtinate Perſons, that will by no means be prevailed with to come over to us, they will however be greatly diſabled, from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching our <hi>Religion,</hi> when they are convinced, that it hath excellent Effects upon the Profeſſors of it. Nor would that idle and ſenceleſs Talk, whereby ſome hot-headed People en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to prove us an <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Church, be by many, if by any liſtned to, if they could diſcern among us more <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Lives; could they be once ſatisfied, that we eſteem it our principal Intereſt and Concernment to make our ſelves and others really and ſubſtantially good,</q> Miniſters by preaching, and all by obeying the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:58738:40"/>
               <p>This would be the moſt likely way to ſecure us from <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> on the one hand; from popular Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and Confuſions, on the other; from all thoſe Evils and Calamities, that threaten us in theſe cloudy, lowring Times, theſe times of general Trouble, and Diſtraction, and abodings of Evil; when <hi>Mens Hearts are ready to fail for fear of what is coming upon the Earth,</hi> what is likely to befal us of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; becauſe this is the ſure way to have the <hi>Soveraign</hi> over-ruling <hi>Power</hi> of Heaven and Earth on our ſide, his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Providence to guard, and defend us in the greateſt Extremities: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the worſe the times are, the greater the Dangers we are in, the more cloſly ſhould we walk with God, in the daily practice of Piety and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, humbling our ſelves for our Sins paſt, and watching againſt future Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, praying for, and putting our Truſt in the Divine Protection, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that excellent Example of the Prophet <hi>Micah;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. 7. ver. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe the Times</hi> were very wicked and perilous, (as <hi>God</hi> knows ours are) Therefore, ſaith he, <hi>I will look unto the Lord, I will wait for the God of my Salvation;</hi> and then he
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58738:41"/>encourageth himſelf in Almighty Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>my God will hear me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beloved, Our <hi>fervent Prayers,</hi> and our <hi>patient continuance in well-doing,</hi> will avail more, for the removal or the prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of publick Calamities, than the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of our States-men, the Zeal of our Preachers; and much more than the heady and inconſiderate endeavours of our People: For when neither the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of our <hi>Counſellours,</hi> nor the <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> of our <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> can preſerve us; God's Mercy doth <hi>deliver the Iſland of the Innocent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 22: 30.</note> 
                  <hi>and it is delivered by the pureneſs of their Hands;</hi> As it was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon another occaſion.<note place="margin">Wiſdom 5.23.</note> 
                  <hi>But Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity ſhall lay waſte the whole Earth, and ill dealing ſhall overthrow the Thrones of the Mighty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this time of general Diſtreſs, Fear, and Danger, every Man almoſt, to be ſure, every <hi>Party</hi> of Men are projecting and fore-caſting this and the other way, to ſecure their own Intereſts; but alaſs, there is but one way to ſave our ſelves, every part, and the <hi>whole;</hi> and that is the way of God, the way we have been commending to you; the way of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, the way of Holineſs, that is, the way of Peace, and Happineſs; Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58738:41"/>are they that walk in it; <hi>Integrity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs will preſerve them, and keep them from the Paths of the Deſtroyer.</hi> If (while we eſcape other Perſecutions) the Calumnies and Reproaches of thoſe that <hi>reproach God,</hi> and his Religion, <hi>fall upon us;</hi> Let us conſider that in due time, <hi>the lying Lips ſhall be put to ſilence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 31.18.</note> 
                  <hi>which ſpeak grievous things proudly and contemptuouſly againſt the Righteous;</hi> or elſe, <hi>God will hide them in the ſecret of his Preſence, from the Pride of Man:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 31.20.</note> 
                  <hi>and keep them ſecretly in a Pavilion from the Strife of-Tongues.</hi> If we <hi>walk in God's Name,</hi> he will preſerve ours, he will give Honour to our Perſons, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to our Cauſe: When <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam</hi> in a Seditious Humour muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> then God is pleaſed to own and vindicate <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Fidelity, and to maintain his Cauſe;<note place="margin">Numb. 12.7.</note> 
                  <hi>My Servant</hi> Moſes <hi>is faithful in all my Houſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then were you not afraid to ſpeak againſt him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any thing will ſhame or confound the Malice of our Enemies, it muſt be an exemplary Piety in our Lives, and Faithfulneſs in our Places.</p>
               <p>We have heretofore, and of late, had many heavy Complaints of <hi>perſecuting Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencers;</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:58738:42"/>but there is one way of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Adverſaries to <hi>Silence,</hi> which ſure will never be accounted <hi>Perſecution;</hi> and that is meerly by <hi>our well-doing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For even thoſe who will ſcarce ſuffer the Word of <hi>Exhortation,</hi> the greateſt Perſuaſions of our Miniſtry, will yield a little to the Integrity and Innocency of our Lives. Therefore however they eſcape the Rod of the Civil <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> or the <hi>Churches Cenſures;</hi> let them not want ſuch Chriſtian Reproofs and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions as theſe. Let the Peoples Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, as well as our Doctrines, ſhew the Folly and Unreaſonableneſs of thoſe that ſeparate from our Communion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the pretence of greater Purity. So that if we do not reclaim thoſe that are at <hi>Rome,</hi> we ſhall be no <hi>Acceſſories</hi> to their Guilt, and clear our ſelves from all ſuſpicion of being at <hi>Rome alſo,</hi> by lending any Hand to advance or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the <hi>Antichriſtianiſm</hi> of that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>I ſhall come next to the ſecond Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="sermon">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:58738:42"/>
               <head>The Fourth Sermon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ROM. 1.15.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>So as much as in me is, I am ready to preach the Goſpel to you that are at <hi>Rome</hi> alſo.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe ſecond Propoſition we are to ſpeak to, was this, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>That the moſt Chriſtian and effectual way of promoting the Goſpel, is Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Perſwaſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is one of the greateſt Glories of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, that it came in, and prevailed in the World upon its own Piety, and Wiſdom, with no Force but a Torrent of Arguments, and <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Spirit;</hi> according to that Prophecy concerning our Saviour,<note place="margin">Iſa. 42.</note> 
                  <hi>That he ſhould ſhew Judgment to the Gentiles, and yet that he ſhould not ſtrive nor ory, i.e.</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:58738:43"/>diſcover no ſign of Anger or Diſcompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in his Mind, nor <hi>That any Man ſhould hear his Voice in the Streets, i.e.</hi> he ſhould raiſe no Tumult or popular Hubbub.</p>
               <p>Again it was prophecied of the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> Days, that our Saviour's Inſtitutions ſhould tend ſo much to the correcting and qualifying of the Ferity and Rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Men's Manners; that they ſhould need no other Weapons of Hoſtility, than thoſe of Argument and Perſwaſion; <hi>That their Swords ſhould be turned into Plow-ſhares, and their Spears into Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-hooks;</hi> and however in this unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Declenſion of Times, Men's World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Intereſts, have much perverted this moſt excellent Deſign of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> yet our bleſſed Lord hath expreſly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned, that whoſoever ſhall preſume to draw the Sword in his Cauſe, ſhall be ſure to periſh by it. The Precepts which he gives, and moſt earneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends, in order to the general Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Mankind, are thoſe of <hi>Meekneſs, Mercy, Forbearance, Long-Suffering, Brotherly Kindneſs,</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi> He gave <hi>Love</hi> for the Livery, and Badg of his Diſciples.<note place="margin">Joh. 13.35.</note> 
                  <hi>By this ſhall all Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58738:43"/>that ye are my Diſciples, if ye love one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> deſcended in the Form of a Dove, to ſignify, ſay ſome, the Meekneſs and Gentleneſs of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Temper. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, that the <hi>Fruit of the Spirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.22, 23.</note> is <hi>Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs, Temperance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Apoſtles of Chriſt,</hi> and their Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, acted upon their <hi>Maſters</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and by the Motions of his <hi>Spirit;</hi> at his <hi>Command</hi> they preached the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> throughout the World, but oppoſed nothing, beſides their Patience and Prayers, to the <hi>Countermands of Civil Authority,</hi> not allowing ſo much as the <hi>Rebellion,</hi> either of the Tongue, or Pen, any open defaming, or any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ways of deſtroying the <hi>Powers</hi> they lived under; <hi>Nunquam Conjuratio crupit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertul. <hi>ad</hi> Nar.</note> they were never found to be in any <hi>Plot,</hi> or treaſonable Conſpiracy; On the contrary being <hi>reviled, they bleſſed,</hi> being <hi>perſecuted, they ſuffered it.</hi> Yea,<note place="margin">Sozom. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> the Calmneſs and Gentlenſs of their Spirit, appeared no leſs afterwards when they were in <hi>Power,</hi> than when under <hi>Perſecution.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:58738:44"/>
               <p>And herein, there Practice was very conformable to the Doctrine of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Men of the firſt Ages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non eſt Religionis, cogere Religionem,</hi> Religion is not to be propagated by Force and Violence,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad</hi> Scapulat.</note> ſaith <hi>Tertullian,;</hi> And it was St. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi>'s Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in his <hi>Oration for Peace,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Chriſtians</hi> muſt overcome their Enemies by leſſening themſelves and lay the Grounds of their higheſt Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs in their loweſt Submiſſions: Our Religion,<note place="margin">Lact. <hi>lib.</hi> 5.</note> ſaith <hi>Lactantius,</hi> muſt be defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>non occidendo, ſed moriendo,</hi> not by taking away other Mens Lives, but by laying down our own, in the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Truth,</hi> and a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whenſoever the Neceſſities of the Church ſhall require it of us.</p>
               <p>It was a great Honour to <hi>Proclus</hi> his <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> that he got the Hearts of his People, and the Ends of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by his admirable Condeſcenſions, and Clemency;<note place="margin">In Vit. <hi>Procli.</hi> Archs. Epiſ. <hi>Conſtant.</hi> ante Opora. <hi>p. 34.</hi>
                  </note> and this was the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Meekneſs, <hi>Ne Oves truci mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacique vultu abſterrendo Lupis parare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Praedam,</hi> leſt by too much Sternneſs and Severity, he ſhould fright the Sheep from the Flock, and thereby make them a more eaſie Prey for the Wolf.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:58738:44"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Manſuetudine corpus Chriſti, quod eſt Eccleſia, vincit Inimicos;</hi> The Churches Meekneſs breaks the Force of her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Rage, and ſhe conquers altogether by Acts of Gentleneſs and <hi>Perſwaſion;</hi> and indeed other Methods are improper, nay ineffectual; Men may be forced into Hypocriſie, but not into a true Belief; they may be beaten out of their Trenches, and out-works of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but the <hi>Devils ſtrongeſt hold,</hi> the <hi>Heart</hi> will not be taken by <hi>Violence;</hi> Nothing can enter there, but the Light of Reaſon, and the <hi>Demonſtration</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the voice of the Wiſe Charmer, and the powerful Preacher, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of Men, and the Grace of God.</p>
               <p>We muſt indeed <hi>contend earneſtly for the Faith,</hi> yet <hi>above all things we muſt put on Charity,</hi> and uſe ſuch other Arms as are fit for the <hi>Chriſtian Warfare,</hi> not thoſe that are <hi>carnal,</hi> but <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> Preaching and Diſputation, Holineſs of Life, Aſſiduity of Exhortation, the word of God, and Prayer; and when we come to reprove, rebuke, and to inflict ſpiritual Puniſhments, we muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh as tenderly as we can, between the wilful and the weak, the obſtinate,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:58738:45"/>and the ignorant: The firſt ſort indeed muſt be more roundly dealt withal;<note place="margin">Iſa. 58.1.</note> It was with ſuch the Prophet <hi>Iſa.</hi> had to do, when God bids him <hi>lift up his Voice like a Trumpet;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.8.</note> with ſuch <hi>Timothy</hi> muſt <hi>be inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, reprove, rebuke with all Authority.</hi> The obſtinate we muſt endeavour <hi>to ſave with fear, plucking them out of the Fire,</hi> with them we muſt be more ſharp and ſevere in our Admonitions and Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; but on the <hi>Weak we muſt have Compaſſion,</hi> thoſe who may be ſuppoſed <hi>affectu piae Opinionis errare,</hi> as <hi>Salvian</hi> thought charitably of ſome <hi>Arrians</hi> of his days; thoſe who as Sheep going aſtray, who may be ſuppoſed to err through ſimplicity, or the Fervours of Devotion, ought to be treated with a fatherly Tenderneſs, and reſtored if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſible with the Spirit of Meekneſs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy, in Meekneſs inſtructing thoſe who oppoſe;</hi> much more thoſe who only peaceably withdraw themſelves, <hi>if God peradventure</hi> will give them <hi>Repentance to the acknowledging of the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Council of <hi>Aix</hi> compares the Church to a Dove, which ſometimes may ſtrike gently with her Wings,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58738:45"/>yet hath neither Beak nor Talons, to tear and deſtroy.</p>
               <p>And it was once the ſaying of a wiſe States-Man,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lord</hi> Verulam.</note> and one not diſaffected to our <hi>Church;</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That there is no better way to ſtop the riſings of new <hi>Sects,</hi> and <hi>Schiſms,</hi> than to reform Abuſes, to compound the ſmaller Differences, to proceed mildly and not with San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary Perſecutions.</q> And God be thankful, ſuch is the preſent Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitution,</hi> that we have no Laws, like thoſe of <hi>Braco,</hi> written in Blood; our Penalties are not for <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> but for Correction and Amendment; we puniſh none for bare Opinions, and readily embrace every returning Penitent: Yea ſuch of late hath been the Tenderneſs and Indulgence of our Gracious King, and our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; that <hi>Mercy</hi> hath triumphed over <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have had more Favour ſhewed them than the <hi>Laws</hi> allow; yet too many of them are as quernlous and diſcontented ſtill as ever, like froward humorous Children that cry, not becauſe they are whipped, but becauſe they may not ſcratch their Nurſe, and have their fooliſh Wills in every thing; or complain of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:58738:46"/>Rigor, though her Commands are very reaſonable, and her Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as gentle: But this we are not to wonder at;<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Puller</hi> of the Moderation of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> for ſince, <q rend="margQuotes">The very mildneſs and gentleneſs of our Lord Chriſt, by which St. <hi>Paul</hi> affectionately entreats the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.1.</note> too ineffectually pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails on the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World, why ſhould we think it ſtrange that the <hi>Moderation,</hi> which is the proper Glory of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> cannot perſwade either the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> or <hi>Enthnſinſts,</hi> to be ſenſible of that <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and Law of Kindneſs, which attempers all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and Conſtitutions of our <hi>Church,</hi>
                  </q> but the vehement Oppoſition of both Extreams confeſſeth, whether they will or no, that we are in the mean, and preſerve that Moderation in our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Doctrines, and our Exerciſe of Diſcipline, which condemns the ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Opinion, and the violence Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in each Party; and ſhews that we cannot joyn with either of them, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Men's Lives, and Fortunes, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning of <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>States, Laws</hi> and <hi>Governments;</hi> much leſs in depoſing or murdering of <hi>Soveraign Princes,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> But this by the way, my Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58738:46"/>at preſent being not ſo much to juſtify the Practice of our Church, as the Doctrine of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and to ſhew that the <hi>Religion</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> made no forcible Entry, upon the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Men; it did not arreſt their Judgments, with Motives drawn from the <hi>civil Power,</hi> ſince it met with the greateſt Oppoſition imaginable, from <hi>the Heathen Emperours;</hi> but had the true Characters of the Divine Preſence, and came peaceably <hi>in aurd leni,</hi> without Noiſe and Perturbation, inſinuating it ſelf into the Beliefs of Men by ſilent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences, and convincing Arguments.</p>
               <p>I may add here, That although our <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> was not only <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> but had the whole Hoſt of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at his command, yet he called not in the Aſſiſtance of Force and Violence, to obtrude his Doctrines upon the World: And it is a moſt remarkable Circumſtance, That <hi>Conſtantine the Great</hi> did not appear in the World to protect <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> until it had gained Footing in the moſt conſiderable Parts thereof; Nor do we read any where, That when <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> became the Religion of the <hi>Empire,</hi> They ever uſed their Power,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:58738:47"/>to revenge their Sufferings, that they ever put either <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Heathen</hi> to Death, becauſe they would not renounce their Religion.</p>
               <p>The Kingdom of <hi>Satan,</hi> and of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> have ſtill been planted and wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Blood and Crueltv. As <hi>Nebr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> once dealt with thoſe who would not Worſhip his Golden <hi>Gods;</hi> ſo did the <hi>Heathen</hi> Emperors with the Primitive <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euſch. <hi>An.</hi> 403.</note> in a long Series of moſt mercileſs Perſecutions. So did the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Perſia,</hi> with <hi>Abdas</hi> the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> who had overturned his <hi>Idol-Temples;</hi> So do the <hi>Turks</hi> at this Day, with all the Oppoſers of their <hi>Superſtition.</hi> And it is ſad to relate the Barbarous Cruelties of ſome profeſſed <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> towards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers really and truly ſuch; how bloody the Rage of the <hi>Arrians</hi> was againſt the <hi>Catholicks;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Athan.</hi> Ep. ad ſol. vit. agentes.</note> as likewiſe that of the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> and <hi>Circumcellians,</hi> in St. <hi>Anguſtine;</hi> that of the <hi>Eutichians,</hi> in the ſecond Council of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> called <hi>Epheſinum Latrocinium,</hi> who murdered <hi>Flavianus, Arch-Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> To come nearer home; I ſhall name no more here, but that of our zealous <hi>Regicides,</hi> which ought to be to us <hi>this day,</hi> and will be to ſucceeding Ages for a <hi>Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:58738:47"/>
               <p>Theſe were the bloody ways of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> and <hi>Hereticks.</hi> But no Hiſtories do tell us, That true <hi>Catholicks</hi> did ever practiſe, or approve of ſuch Methods of maintaining, or propagating <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Pſeudo-Roman-Catholicks</hi> indeed, are upon infamous Record, for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane Cruelties in the defence of their <hi>Churches</hi> Errors and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations:</hi> which ſpeaks the <hi>Pope,</hi> the Succeſſor of <hi>Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> who made his way by Blood, rather than of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who drew his Sword but once in his <hi>Maſter</hi>'s Quarrel, and was ſeverely checked by him for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>When the War, begun by the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> on the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Saracens,</hi> was turned upon the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> by the <hi>Popes</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Heylin's</hi> Parable of the Tares.</note> and that the <hi>Cruciata</hi> was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed againſt thoſe poor Souls only, becauſe they differed in ſome Points of Doctrine, from the Opinions of that <hi>Church;</hi> how many hundred thouſands, of well meaning Men, who made a Conſcience of their ways, and erred not (if they erred at all) out of Pride, but Ignorance, fell a Sacrifice to the <hi>Roman Furies?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:58738:48"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thuanus</hi> their own Hiſtorian, reports that Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the third,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anno</hi> 1559.</note> among other Exhortations, which upon his Death-Bed he delivered to his <hi>Cardinals,</hi> did laſtly wiſh them to uphold the Office of the <hi>Inquiſition, quo uno ſacro-ſactam authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem niti affirmabant,</hi> whereby the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is chiefly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, with the <hi>French Papiſts,</hi> never acted any thing with more Satisfaction to his <hi>Holineſs,</hi> than that <hi>Tragedy</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> and other <hi>Cities,</hi> where ſo many thouſand <hi>Hugonots,</hi> were moſt treacherouſly and barbarouſly ſlaughtered.</p>
               <p>The Savage <hi>Iriſh,</hi> never thought their Hands and Weapons better em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, than in butchering the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants;</hi> and this not more from the fierceneſs of their Natures, than from the bloody Principles of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>And in our own Nation, how many ſuffered Death under King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th,</hi> and in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s, his bloody Daughter's Days, for their moſt reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Unbelief of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have not now time to bring to your remembrance, the many Conſpiracies
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58738:48"/>of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> againſt, and Attempts upon the Life of our <hi>bleſſed Queen Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> by <hi>Parry, Babington, Stafford, Lopez, Squire,</hi> &amp;c. Nor to preſent you with the horrid Circumſtances of their <hi>Powder Treaſon,</hi> againſt King <hi>James</hi> her peaceful <hi>Succeſſour,</hi> all the Royal Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with the Flower of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> in a <hi>Parliament</hi> Aſſembly.</p>
               <p>But I wiſh we would take ſpecial notice, by reaſon of the ſeaſonableneſs of the reflection of their treaſonable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and Actings, againſt that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable <hi>Prince, Charles</hi> the Firſt, this Days <hi>Martyr;</hi> How they plotted againſt his Life, and Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi>'s, as hath formerly, and of late, been ſufficiently diſcovered; how they blowed the Coales of the late unnatural and deſtructive War; how in their Conſults, they voted that King's Death as much conducing to the Intereſt of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Cauſe, as they call theirs; and how they aſſiſted and directed Inſtruments, whereby that Helliſh Enterprize (for which we and the whole Nation mourn this day) was accompliſhed, and how they tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed thereupon; all this is notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly known.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:58738:49"/>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">The firſt Rebellion began in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See the Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in behalf of the Papiſts an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, in behalf of the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alists. <hi>p. 12. London, 1667.</hi>
                     </note> where the Deſign of it was laid by <hi>Cardinal Richlieu,</hi> his <hi>Majeſties</hi> irreconcileable Enemy; Then it brake out in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where it was bleſſed with his <hi>Holineſs</hi>'s Letters, and aſſiſted by his <hi>Nuncio,</hi> whom he ſent purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to attend the Fire there; Laſtly, in <hi>England,</hi> as hath been intimated, it is manifeſt their Agents did their parts there to unſettle the People, and gave them needleſs occaſions of Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, which the vigilant Phanaticks made uſe of, to involve us all in War and Confuſion: Both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> the ſpecial Tools they wrought with, were borrowed out of the Shops of the <hi>Romans.</hi> It was our <hi>Royal Martyr</hi>'s own Obſervation,<note place="margin">Large Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Tumults in <hi>Scotland.</hi> p. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> That their Maximes were the ſame with the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> their Preachers Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons were delievered in the very Phraſe of <hi>Becanus, Sciopius,</hi> and <hi>Eudae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Johannes,</hi> their poor Arguments printed, or written in their ſeditious Pamphlets, were taken almoſt verba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim out of <hi>Bellarmin,</hi>
                  </q> or <hi>Suarez;</hi> and afterwards we have heard how they carried on, and compleated the bloody Tragedy, by <hi>Popiſh</hi> Influence and Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:58738:49"/>
               <p>Hath the Clemency and Indulgence of his <hi>Majeſty</hi> who now is, and whom God long preſerve, any ways aſſwaged their Malice and turned their Hearts to better Purpoſes?</p>
               <p>Their late deep and dreadful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy againſt the ſacred Life of ſo good and <hi>Gracious a Prince,</hi> and the whole body of his <hi>Proteſtant Subjects,</hi> returns a loud <hi>Negative</hi> to the Queſtion; and gives us too ſad and ſenſible an Aſſurance that <hi>their Feet are ſtill ſwift to ſhed Blood, that Deſtruction and Miſery are in their ways; and the ways of Peace have they not known.</hi> And I would there was no juſt cauſe of Fear, that they are working our Ruine again by the very Inſtruments they uſed ſo ſucceſsfully heretofore, and that ſome of thoſe that give us the loudeſt <hi>Alarms</hi> of the <hi>Romans</hi> coming to take away our Place and Nation, are not themſelves preparing their way. But are the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> indeed among all our modern Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> the only <hi>Anti-Goſpelers</hi> in this particular of promoting Religion by Force? Truly I believe, the bloody and rebellious Principles of all others, were <hi>originally</hi> theirs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from them.</p>
               <p>But we can by no means excuſe the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:58738:50"/>Tyranny of the <hi>Independency,</hi> of which we read ſo much in the Hiſtory that bears its Name; And their fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent putting <hi>Quakers</hi> to death in New <hi>England</hi> for their Opinions,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Thorndike's</hi> Forbearance of Penalttes. <hi>c. 29.</hi>
                  </note> doth ſhew what a meek, merciful Spirit they are of, and what Liberties they are like to allow others, wherever they obtain Rule; And I wiſh with all my heart, I could honeſtly ſpeak better, and more gentle things of all their elder Brethren, the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> and becauſe many of that Perſwaſion, are not only ſound, and Orthodox in the main <hi>Articles</hi> of our <hi>reformed Religion,</hi> but learned, and able Defenders of it, zealous Proteſtours againſt the horrid Wickedneſs of this <hi>Day,</hi> and active Inſtruments in bringing home our baniſhed <hi>King;</hi> I am not willing to ſay the worſt I know of the violence of ſome of their Spirits, and the ſeverity of their Diſcipline. Yet I hope none among us will juſtify the Rage, Malice, and Cruelties of the Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field-Meeters, ten of whom barbarouſly murdered the <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> of St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews;</hi> and it is the current Doctrine of their Pulpits and Books, that killing of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and thoſe ordained by them, is no Murder, but a commendable, yea an
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58738:50"/>Heroical Act of Juſtice; and that a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting <hi>Covenanter</hi> of any ſort is as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable a <hi>Sacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Altho I fear too many among us feel ſome glowings of this <hi>Helliſh Zeal,</hi> ſome kindlings and ſtirrings of this fiery fierce Spirit, yet (bleſſed be God) they have hitherto, and I hope ſtill will be reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from ſuch outragious Villanies.</p>
               <p>But let me not I beſeech you be thought your <hi>Enemy, If I tell you the Truth,</hi> in telling you plainly; That thus far we muſt complain of the ſeverity, their want of a <hi>Goſpel-Spirit,</hi> as <hi>Optatus</hi> did of ſome <hi>ſeparating,</hi> ſlandering Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents of his time, <hi>Dei Epiſcopos lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guae Gladio jugulaſtis, fundentes Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem non Corporis ſed Honoris.</hi> Though your hands have ſpared the <hi>Lives,</hi> yet your Tongues have murdered the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation</hi> of Gods <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and Miniſters; though you have not ſhed their Blood, yet you have ſtained their <hi>Honour,</hi> and which is worſe vilified, their <hi>Function;</hi> yea notwithſtanding the undeniable and convincing Proofs they have given, both heretofore and of late, by their Preachings, Writings, and Practices of their Sincerity in, and <hi>Zeal</hi> for the Proteſtant Religion, yet as <hi>Tacitus</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:58738:51"/>ſpeaks,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tacitus</hi> In Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tá <hi>Agricol.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>conflatâ magnâ invidiâ, ſeu bene ſeu male geſta premunt,</hi> Where Envy and Spite predominate, Mens good or bad Actions are alike diſtaſtful; and what was ſaid out of the ſame Author in <hi>Proclus</hi>'s Caſe,<note place="margin">Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Procl.</hi> p. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> that famous <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> may well be applied to theirs: <hi>Non minus eſt periculum in magnâ quam in mala fama, cum fumma ſemper petat livor,</hi> It is not the Evil of their <hi>Lives,</hi> nor the Errour of their <hi>Doctrines,</hi> but the eminency of their <hi>Place,</hi> if not of their <hi>Vertues,</hi> which hath drawn upon them ſo much vulgar hatred and <hi>Obloquy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Faults they have had,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Barrow's <hi>Ser. on</hi> Pſal. 132.16.</note> and will always have, for they are Men, and ſubject to the common Imperfections of mortal Nature, but that perhaps leſs and fewer than any other diſtinct ſort of Men; But if their Faults were greater than ever they have really been, or than ever Malice could miſrepreſent them; is it therefore equal, that the Miſcarriages of ſome ſhould derogate from the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Prejudice the Welfare of the whole Order? yet ſo blind, as well as bitter is ſome Men's Zeal, that they think they do God and their Country good Service, in purſuing them all with
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:58738:51"/>the ſame cry, and running them down together with an indiſcriminating Rage; as if they were the greateſt Enemies of our Peace and Proſperity, and that there were a touch of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> in all our Evils, and Inconveniencies. But without offering at any Vindication, (which indeed would be beſides my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Purpoſe) it may not be amiſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, for the furthering the Humiliation of <hi>this Day,</hi> to conſider, that they who began with the <hi>Church</hi> before, ended with the Crown; and tho at firſt they pretended a Quarrel only with our <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy,</hi> they ſoon proceeded to <hi>pour Contempt upon Princes</hi> and <hi>Nobles,</hi> and to make havock of <hi>Royalty</hi> it ſelf; and that when it was moſt happily ſeated in ſo Wiſe, ſo Holy, and ſo Gracious a <hi>King,</hi> and all under a great ſhew of Zeal for the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and the Purity of <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But how far this was from the true and genuine Spirit of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> from the Doctrine of our Saviour, and the Acts of his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> may be eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred from what you have heard; and particularly from the Practice of our St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who tho when a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> he thought he did <hi>God</hi> and Religion <hi>good
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58738:52"/>Service,</hi> in perſecuting the <hi>Church;</hi> yet when once a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> he thinks only of preaching the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> He who before <hi>breathed out nothing but Threatnings and Slaughter;</hi> after his Converſion, only <hi>exhorts, entreats with all Long-ſuffering,</hi> and <hi>beſeecheth by the Mercies of God;</hi> Not that our Apoſtle was leſs concerned for the Intereſts of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> than for thoſe of his former <hi>Religion,</hi> but better inſtructed in the way of promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them, <hi>viz.</hi> by the <hi>Miniſtry of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation,</hi> preaching among the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles the unſearchable Riches of Chriſt,</hi> and by propounding the great Benefits and Bleſſings of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as the moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Advocates for its Entertainment, and if at any time he makes uſe of the <hi>Terrors of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.11.</note> it is not to <hi>perſecute,</hi> but to <hi>perſwade</hi> Men.</p>
               <p>How far Civil Magiſtrates may by Threatnings and Puniſhments compel Men to ſerve <hi>God,</hi> and keep <hi>his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> is not the matter of our preſent Enquiry, we ſee what is the proper Duty of thoſe of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and what work is like to proſper beſt in their hands, when they have to do either with thoſe at <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other <hi>Sects</hi> of Erroneous <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> viz.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58738:52"/>Diligence and Faithfulneſs in <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel;</hi> and ſo I come to the third and laſt Particular.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>That thoſe who are commiſſionated to the Office of the Miniſtry, ought to be ready, and reſolute in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The excellent Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer to the <hi>6</hi> Queries. <hi>p. 365.</hi>
                  </note> hath well obſerved that the whole well-being of the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> which conſiſts in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> as the well-being of a Body, in the Health of it; nay, the very Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf, which conſiſts in the Truth of the Doctrines, and Obedience to the Inſtitutions of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> depends in an eminent manner upon the due Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of thoſe who are intruſted with the Office of Teaching, in the <hi>Church;</hi> and although the beſt of us are not ſufficient for ſo worthy an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, yet the worſt of us are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to do our beſt, and to <hi>be ready as much as in us lies,</hi> to preach <hi>the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, to reaſon</hi> according to our Ability, and Proportion, as our great <hi>Apoſtle</hi> did <hi>of Temperance</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs and Judgment to come, and ſhewing out of a good Converſation, our Works with meekneſs of Wiſdom, taking heed unto our
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58738:53"/>ſelves and to our Doctrine</hi> that in ſo <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we may both ſave our ſelves,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.16. 2 Tim. 2.15.</note> 
                  <hi>and them that hear us.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.24, 25, 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Studying to ſhew our ſelves</hi> appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>unto God,</hi> Work-men <hi>that need not to be aſhamed, rightly dividing the Word of Truth; being gentle unto all Men, apt to teach, patient in Meekneſs, inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure will give them Repentance, to the acknowledging of the Truth, and that they may recover themſelves out of the Snare of the Devil, who are taken Captive by his Will;</hi> as our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> exhorts <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We muſt not be wanting in declaring to our People the <hi>whole Counſel of God;</hi> being ready to inſtruct the Ignorant, and to reduce the Erroneous by all good Means, and to fortity them, what we can, againſt the Aſſaults and Artifices of Seducers, who <hi>lie in wait to deceive,</hi> and make a Prey of them; and more eſpecially at this Time, to fore-warn them of the great Evils and Dangers of <hi>Popery:</hi> That whilſt the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> take care to ſecure all the Publick Intereſts, by Inſtruments of their own; we alſo may, by the Word of our proper Miniſtry, endeavour to ſtop the Progreſſion of ſuch <hi>Errors,</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:58738:53"/>which, as we have heard, are ſo very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, and hurtful to the Souls of Men; perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding withal, what we can, to Unity and brotherly Agreement among our ſelves, that we may thereby ſtrengthen and double our Guards, againſt ſo powerful and Subtil an Enemy.</p>
               <p>If the Credit of <hi>Religion,</hi> the Glory of <hi>God,</hi> the Souls of our <hi>Brethren,</hi> be dear unto us; what can we do leſs, than by a juſt and mild Defence of the Truth, ſeek the Reclaiming of ſuch as are gone aſtray, and the Eſtabliſhment of them who are weak in Judgment, but ſincere in Affection, willing <hi>in all things to live honeſtly and peaceably?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How much doth it concern us, by conſtant <hi>Pain,</hi> full <hi>Catechiſing,</hi> and <hi>Preaching,</hi> firſt to ground and inſtruct ſimple <hi>People</hi> in the Religion of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> the Principles of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> and then to inform them of the <hi>Devices</hi> of <hi>Satan,</hi> the wily Methods of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors, leſt by <hi>fair Words,</hi> and <hi>enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Speeches,</hi> they <hi>beguile the Hearts of the Simple and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwary?</hi> It concerns us, to warn Men of the infectious and dangerous Nature of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> the vile and pernicious
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:58738:54"/>Deſigns of ſome plauſible Pretenders to Holineſs, and the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> (which every truly Chriſtian Heart cannot but paſſionately regret) who go about to turn Men to another <hi>Goſpel,</hi> by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting firſt the <hi>Scripture,</hi> the <hi>Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Life, Death, Reſurrection,</hi> and <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> of our Lord Chriſt, into vain and fantaſtical <hi>Allegories;</hi> as it is too notoriouſly known, the <hi>Familiſts</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times did, and more than a Suſpicion that the <hi>Quakers</hi> do at preſent. Theſe things would be plainly repreſented to the leſs knowing Parts of our Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and all together would be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly and ſoberly told of the Danger of <hi>Popery, Socinianiſm,</hi> as well as <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſtical</hi> Pretenſions; there being a conſiderable Number of each Faction driving on their diſtinct Intereſts among us, and have already <hi>turned many from the Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But becauſe this way of publick Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and Admonition, is more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my ſingle Duty, than any others in this Place; and becauſe I hope I have in a good meaſure diſcharged it at this Time; and being <hi>ready</hi> alſo, with God's gracious Aſſiſtance, as <hi>mnch as in me lies,</hi> to purſue it upon all fitting Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58738:54"/>I ſhall conclude my <hi>Preaching</hi> with a twofold <hi>Prayer:</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. To You, my beloved Hearers; and then,</item>
                     <item>2. To Almighty God: And to both in the Words of our <hi>Apostle.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, to you who hear me this day; <hi>That you would mark them which cauſe Diviſions,</hi> or broach Errors,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine which you have heard, and avoid them; And I beſeech you by the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that there be no Diviſions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10.</note> 
                  <hi>or Schiſms amongſt you but that you be perfectly joyned together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame Judgment.</hi> That inſtead of repining at little Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, you would be much, and frequent in ſerious Thankfulneſs to our <hi>moſt merciful Father,</hi> for the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, Purity, and Peace of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> praying to God (which is all you have to do) that thoſe things which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs either in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State</hi> may be better, and praiſing him that they are no worſe; This I beg of you, in the next place.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:58738:55"/>
               <p n="2">2. I ſhall pray to <hi>Almighty God,</hi> (and I hope that you will all joyn heartily with me,)<note place="margin">Rom. 15.5.</note> that the <hi>God of Patience will grant you</hi> to be like <hi>minded one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after the example of Jeſus Chriſt, that you may with one mind and with one mouth glorifie God, even the</hi> Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now the Lord in Mercy look down from Heaven upon his</hi> Church <hi>and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful People; bring his Truth to light more and more, diſpel the Miſts of Ignorance, remove all Occaſions of Offence, ſettle Peace and Truth, proſper the Means of Grace, build us up in Faith and Holineſs, and unite the Hearts of his People in Love, that they may direct their Courſe by one Rule, walk in one Way, until we all receive the End of our Faith, the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Souls, through</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>our Lord, to Whom, with the Father, and the Holy-Ghost, be all Honour, Glory, and Praiſe, now and for evermore,</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:58738:55"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 27. line 1. for <hi>Dominick,</hi> reade <hi>Damian.</hi> P. 62. l. 32. reade <hi>Amyraut.</hi> P. 67. l. 20. r. <hi>ſhrewdeſt.</hi> l. 9. r. <hi>Deſigners.</hi> P. 82. l. 6. f. <hi>greateſt,</hi> r. <hi>gentleſt.</hi> P. 87. l. 5. f. <hi>Acts,</hi> r. <hi>Arts.</hi> P. 88. l. 16. after <hi>who,</hi> add <hi>are.</hi> P. 89. l. 11. f. <hi>thankfull,</hi> r. <hi>thanked.</hi> l. 13. r. <hi>Draco.</hi> P. 90. l. 22. to <hi>violence,</hi> add <hi>of.</hi> P. 92. l. 22. r. <hi>Circumcellions.</hi> P. 99. l. 13. f. <hi>the,</hi> r. <hi>their.</hi> P. 104. l. 13. add to <hi>by, him at.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
